<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fourth part of naked truth, or, The complaint of the church to some of her sons for breach of her articles in a friendly dialogue between Titus and Timothy, both ministers of the Church of England / by a legal son and since conformist to the Church of England, as established by law.</title>
            <title>Naked truth. Part 4</title>
            <author>Hickeringill, Edmund, 1631-1708.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 222 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43619</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1806</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14467</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12850787</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12850787</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94521</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43619)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94521)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 383:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fourth part of naked truth, or, The complaint of the church to some of her sons for breach of her articles in a friendly dialogue between Titus and Timothy, both ministers of the Church of England / by a legal son and since conformist to the Church of England, as established by law.</title>
                  <title>Naked truth. Part 4</title>
                  <author>Hickeringill, Edmund, 1631-1708.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Janeway ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by E. Hickeringill. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 42.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England. --  Thirty-nine Articles.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94521:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94521:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Fourth Part of Naked Truth: OR, THE COMPLAINT OF THE CHURCH To ſome of Her SONS For breach of HER ARTICLES.</p>
            <p>In a Friendly Dialogue between <hi>TIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> and <hi>TIMOTHY,</hi> both Miniſters of the <hi>Church of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Legal Son, and ſincere Conformiſt to the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>as eſtabliſhed by Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Non recipit mendacium veritas; nec patitur religio impietatem.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>D. Hillar.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Non temerè dico, ſed ut affectus ſum, ac ut ſentio, non arbitror Sacerdotes mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos eſſe, qui ſalvi fiant: ſed multò plures qui pereant.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Chryſ. Hom.</hi> 3. <hi>in Act. Apoſt.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Neque enim aliorum ſalutem ſedulò unquam curabit, qui ſuam negligit.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Calvin.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Janeway,</hi> in <hi>Queens-head Alley</hi> in <hi>Pater-noſter-Row.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:94521:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:94521:2"/>
            <head>Naked Truth, THE FOURTH PART.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Titus.</speaker>
               <p>REverend <hi>Tim,</hi> well met: I have thought long for a little ſerious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with thee; and now opportunity favours me: Come, here a convenient Arbour, let's ſit down and enjoy one another one quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an hour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>Enjoy one another! prithee, I can't enjoy my ſelf.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>Bleſs me! What doſt mean?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>I mean I can't, I won't talk.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>I confeſs you have ſome ill ſymptoms upon you; are you not well, Sir?—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>No, not ſo well as I would be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>Why, who, or what would you be?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>I would be a Biſhop, Dean, Archdeacon, or a fat Paſtor at leaſt.—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>I commend thee <hi>Tim;</hi> as mad as thou art, I ſee thou wilt wiſh no harm to thy ſelf. And though I never reckoned thy Stars ſo lucky, as to exalt thee to a Biſhoprick or Deanary, yet were it not that thy threadbear Caſſock and ſuperannuated Beaver ſuit it not, I ſhould have thought a luſty Parſonage, or plentifully endowed Vicaridge had been thy lot long ere this.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>No in truth, no ſuch plumbs will fall in my diſh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>Where lies thy misfortune?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>In my Conformity, which is too ſcanty; yet I know not any <hi>punctilio</hi> requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, wherein I have fail'd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>Fail'd! no, thou art ſo perfectly innocent in this matter, that if thou wilt call me before the Biſhop, I will witneſs for thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>Witneſs! what will you witneſs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>That which, if any thing, will do you a kindneſs, and help you to your deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red preferment.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>What's that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>In ſhort, I can teſtifie <hi>(verbo Sacerdotis),</hi> that thou art ſo far from being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective, that thou art <hi>redundant,</hi> out-doeſt the Act for Conformity it ſelf in Practice, and many of the 39. Articles in Doctrine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>Good Mr. <hi>Titus,</hi> you make my heart leap within me; I ſhould begin to be proud of my ſelf, if you would but explain your meaning.—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, not too proud <hi>Tim</hi> neither; for you are not the only man doth this, there are many, too many ſuch Conformiſts, beſides you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>Good ſtill; <hi>The more the merrier.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>True, but the <hi>fewer the better cheer.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>Well, but your meaning: You ſay, I (and ſome others) out-do the very Act of Conformity in Practice, and many of the 39. Articles in Doctrine,—Your meaning now?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>That is, in plain <hi>Engliſh,</hi> you uſe thoſe Ceremonies which the Act for Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity enjoyns not; and preach ſuch Doctrines as the Articles of our Church (the ſtanding Rule next the Scriptures for our preaching) allow not. This do you, and many more of our brethren in the Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis eaſily ſaid, but how do you prove it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:94521:3"/>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>The thing proves it ſelf, only by having recourſe to the Act, and to the Articles, and comparing what you do and ſay with theſe touchſtones. But before we meddle with proof, let me ask thee a queſtion or two <hi>Tim,</hi> and prithee anſwer me ſeriouſly; come, here's no body hears but thee and I.—<hi>Firſt,</hi> didſt thou ever peruſe the Act of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>Never in all my life: what need I? I know my duty without reading the Act.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>Huge well no doubt;—Next, did you ever for you never yet were poſſeſſed of a Benefice, though you often poſſeſs the Pulpit for half an hour, or ſo); did you, I ſay, ever ſeriouſly read and conſider the Articles of our Church?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>No, neither.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>But you have ſubſcribed them, have you not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>Yes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>And not read them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>No.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>A hopeful youth; I wiſh you were ſingle: ſubſcribe you know not what! and this makes you preach you know not what; riſe a note beyond <hi>Ela,</hi> and to out do all your ſober brethren, preach down the Doctrines of the Church you ought to maintain, and deſtroy with your tongue what you have ſubſcribed to preſerve with your hand. This makes our enemies on both ſides laugh in their ſleeves, to ſee ſo many profound Drs. ſin for ignorance ſake, and ſome for intereſt ſake rend in peices our very foundations, preach and write contrary to each other, as if the only conteſt were, not who ſhall be the honeſteſt and moſt conſcientious, but the greateſt Church-man: For go to this Congregation, and there Dr. <hi>Socinus</hi> preaches; to that, and there the Reverend <hi>Arminius</hi> holds forth; to a third, and there the much admired <hi>Calvin</hi> is reading a <hi>Geneva</hi> Lecture; yet all of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribers to her Articles.—This is fine indeed, don't you think ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhall think nothing till you come to prove ſomething.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>Well remembred: Firſt then I am to prove, that you (and many more of your Cue) uſe ſome Ceremonies which the Act of Uniformity doth not enjoyn, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently do more than you need, or ſhall have thanks for from our Lawmakers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>Ay that, prove that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>Thus then <hi>Tim;</hi> That Act requires the uſe of no more Ceremonies than are contained and preſcribed in the Book of Common Prayer;
<note place="margin">The Act for Uniform. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roli</hi> 2d. 14.</note> if therefore you uſe any Ceremonies not contained and preſcribed in the Book of Common Prayer, you uſe more than the Act requires—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>What are thoſe Ceremonies contained and preſcribed in the Liturgy or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer-Book?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>The Surplice, the Croſs in Baptiſm, and kneeling at the Sacrament of the Lords Supper.—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>Goodman Ninny, and do I uſe any more than theſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, Goodman Confidence, and more beſides you too.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>Which be they?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>What think you of bowing at the name of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and bowing to or towards the Altar? Are not theſe as much, and as great Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies as either of the former?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>Granted, and as innocent too.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>That's not the caſe, but are they enjoyned? For if ſaying this or that is an inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Ceremony, will juſtifie the making and uſe of it, we may quickly have as many as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> her ſelf; and then what's become of our Reformation; for all her Ceremonies are innocent, her ſelf being Judge?—But where, I ſay again, are theſe required?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>In the Liturgy, are they not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>Not in that which my Church-Wardens bought for me; and they tell me, they are ſure they bought the neweſt Edition.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>I'le proteſt you've ſtunded me; Ple conſider of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>Conſider it! be aſhamed of it; for you tranſgreſs the Law as much in adding to, as in taking from what is contained and preſcribed in the Book of Common Prayer: for the Act eſtabliſheth that, and no other; the Ceremonies therein contained, and no more. For your fuller ſatisfaction read the words of the Act in this point; they are theſe,—<hi>And be it further enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that no form or order of Common-Prayers, adminiſtration of Sacraments, Rites or Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies</hi> (mark that) <hi>ſhall be openly uſed in any Church, Chappel, or other publick place of, or in any Colledg or Hall in either of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, &amp;c. other than what is preſcribed and appointed to be uſed in and by the ſaid Book</hi> (note that alſo). And leſt once mentioning of this ſhould not be ſufficient, you have afterwards (when the ſaid Book, with the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Rites and Ceremonies preſcribed and appointed by it, is named) theſe words (and no other) again repeated.— What think you now <hi>Tim?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>I think bowing towards the Altar, and bowing at the name of Jeſus are works of ſupererogation, and not at all meritorious; For the Act ſeems not only not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn them, but to forbid them, in as much as they are no where contained in the ſaid Book.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>Thus you give offence, and become a ſcandal to weak brethren where you need not, nay in things you ought not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>I ſee it, and hope I
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94521:3"/>ſhall avoid it for the future, and ſhall endeavour, my brethren of the Clergy about me may do the ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>I wiſh they may. But there is that which is far worſe than all this.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>What ſhould that be, brother <hi>Titus?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>Thank you Sir, for that friendly title; I wiſh we of the Clergy were all true brethren in heart and deed; that we might all ſpeak and do the ſame things, as our Rule requires: I am pleaſed, I ſay, with this expreſſion of amity, and 'twill make me the more free in my talk with you, as well as ſerious.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>The more free the more grateful; for you have gained upon me by your plain dealing and ſtrong arguments. Go on brother, with what you were about to ſay was worſe than the addition of thoſe Ceremonies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis this, brother, That many of our publick Preachers, ſome igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly, ſome (I fear) deſignedly, oppoſe and preach down the very Articles of our Church, which they have ſubſcribed, and which we all are bound to maintain and keep cloſe to, which hath been matter of great grief to me to conſider.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>But ſurely there are none do this.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>As ſure as you are there, too many; and, if I miſtake not, you for one, and that too oft.—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>I am not conſcious to my ſelf I do, or ever did.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>I confeſs I have ſo much charity as to think ſo, and that your ſin is a ſin of ignorance, becauſe you ſaid but now, you never read the Articles. Though I muſt tell you, <hi>Tim,</hi> 'tis vincible ignorance; for that you have not read them, is your own fault.—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>No I profeſs, they are ſo ſcarce to be got, that I know not where to have them; and I withal ſo ſhort of money, that I know not how to purchaſe them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>To remove this obſtacle, and cure your ignorance in ſome meaſure, here they are: I hope you can read as well as preach.—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, yes, I am not ſo ignorant neither; pray let me ſee them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>Hold, not without Conditions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>What are they?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, reaſonable enough: Firſt, that you will ſtay ſo long here as to read them over deliberately; and Secondly, admit of a ſhort debate, as we paſs along, upon ſome of them; and then tell me, whether I do any wrong to you and many others, in ſaying, that your Doctrines and theirs do not admirably well agree with them: For I meddle only with thoſe that have ſubſcribed, yet do not keep to them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
               <p>All this is highly reaſonable, and I readily yeild to it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
               <p>Begin then, and read care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, not haſtily.—</p>
            </sp>
            <div n="1" type="article">
               <head>Article 1.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>There is but one living and true God, everlaſting, without body, parts, or paſſions; of infinite power, wiſdom and goodneſs, the maker and preſerver of all things both viſible and inviſible. And in unity of this Godhead there be three perſons, of one ſubſtance, power and eternity, the Father, the Son and the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Hold now, what think you of this Article?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Mighty well, ſound and good, and no body ſurely but believe and approve it, both in part and in whole.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I am afraid not; how elſe come you (and many others) to diſcourſe ſometimes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and deride what is contained in it? I don't mean the being of a God; for tho' ſome in their works (and with <hi>David</hi>'s fool in their hearts) ſay there is no God; yet I know you dare not do it in words. But that which is next door by, they dare and do ſay.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>What's that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>That there is no Providence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Admit it, wherein doth that croſs this Article, that hath not a word of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in it? I don't ſee but a man may think ſo, and yet ſafely ſubſcribe this Article.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Right, 'tis what I expected, and doubtleſs there are many of your judgment; but what if I prove a Divine Providence governing the world, and all that there is; and after that, prove too, that this firſt Article of our Church plainly aſſerts it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Then I ſhall ſay, I never underſtood it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>A worthy ſatisfaction for your groſs, wilful ignorance, and the great miſchief you have thereby done to the Chriſtian Religion, and the Church of God eſtabliſhed amongſt us. Tell me, what think you of thoſe words of our Saviour,
<note place="margin">Mat. 18.29, 30.</note> 
                     <hi>Not a Sparrow falls to the ground without your father; and the hairs of your head are all numbered?</hi> I think this bids fair to prove a protecting, preſerving, diſpoſing providence, and that not only as to the great changes and revolutions in Kingdoms and Nations, but even as to ſmaller matters, ſuch as relate to you, and me, and every man; nay, to the very beaſts and birds. And he that ſhall ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſider the workings of God now in the world, and even in that ſpot of it which we inhabit; and think how the wiſe and profound Polititians of <hi>Rome</hi> are baffled in their enterpriſes, and detected in their helliſh Plots and Counſels, even beyond their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation or belief, muſt either put out the eye of his Reaſon, or elſe he muſt needs ſee and adore a ſpecial hand of Providence acting for us to admiration—What prevented the further deſigned miſchief from taking place, when <hi>London</hi> was put in flames, if pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94521:4"/>did not? How came the late (as well as former) Popiſh Plot againſt King, the Kingdom, our Religion and Lives, to light, but by providence? In a word <hi>Tim,</hi> think, &amp; then ſay, what was the ſafeguard of our preſent gracious Sovereign in many battels, when divers fell on his right hand and left, in ſundry purſuits, and in foreign Countries, and what reſtored him to his Rights, Crowns and people without the leaſt oppoſition, and with an univerſal conſent, and unheard-of acclamations of joy, but wonderful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence? Certainly there was as great a Concatenation of providences in his preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and return, as in the fall and riſe of <hi>Joſeph</hi> (God give his Majeſty an heart to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member and improve it!) or in <hi>Job</hi>'s, <hi>David</hi>'s caſe, or any recorded in holy Writ I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not therefore diſapprove the ingenuous return of a Scholar coming for Orders, and being asked by his Poſer, how he proved a providence, anſwered (it being quickly after the Kings Reſtauration), <hi>redeunte Carolo.</hi> And certainly wanted we other inſtances, that's ſufficient and high enough alone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>This is ſomething, but not enough.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Enough ſurely to any but an <hi>Epicurean.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>An <hi>Epicurean,</hi> what's that? Call me no hard names, if you do, you'll move my Choler.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall be ſorry for that; but if I ſhould, I'le endeavour to make you amends, by laying it again.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Tell me then, why do you call me <hi>Epicurean?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe I take you to be one of <hi>Epicurus</hi> his Scholars.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Epicurus!</hi> who's he? 'Slid! this is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable, <hi>Epicurus,</hi> and <hi>Epicurean!</hi> — Farewel Sir, I'le have no more of this.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Patience man a little, and hear who this <hi>Epicurus</hi> was; He was a certain ancient Gentleman, Tutor to Mr. <hi>Hobbs,</hi> whom I ſuppoſe you well knew.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>You have abated my heate a little, by naming that perſon, worthy Mr. <hi>Hobbs,</hi> profound, non-ſuch Mr. <hi>Hobbs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I knew how to nick you; I know you are well acquainted with his works.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Huge well; I have read them all, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to read them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>More than to read the old doting Fathers, the crabbed Schoolmen, or any modern Divine, not to ſay the Scriptures themſelves?—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I think he that reads <hi>Hobbs,</hi> reads all that is to be read, can be read, or is worth the reading. But what is all this to <hi>Epicuran?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>You miſtake <hi>Tim,</hi> 'tis <hi>Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rean;</hi> and the ſhort is this, Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> denies a providence, he learned it of <hi>Epicurus;</hi> you deny a providence, being taught ſo of Mr. <hi>Hobbs;</hi> and ſo you are either an <hi>Epicurean</hi> or an <hi>Hobbiſt,</hi> which you pleaſe <hi>Tim;</hi> Though I ſtiled you after the firſt, as being the more ancient, and ſo I thought the more honourable.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, if this be all you mean by <hi>Epicurean,</hi> I ſhall own it for Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> and ſake, and am of his opinion, and ſhall be, notwithſtanding what you have urged—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I am ſorry for it; but if what I have inferred from the words of Chriſt prevail not, what think you of the opinion of a grave Divine and good Chriſtian?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I don't know, who is it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>One that no doubt underſtood the Articles of our Church very well;
<note place="margin">Herb, <hi>on Provid.</hi>
                     </note> hear what he ſaith, and you will judge who I mean—</p>
               </sp>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O ſacred Providence, who from end to end,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Strongly and ſweetly moveſt! ſhall I write,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And not of thee, through whom my fingers bend</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To hold my Quill? ſhall they not do thee right?</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of all the Creatures</hi>—</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Hold, here's enough, 'tis <hi>Herbert,</hi> but little to my conviction.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I was afraid ſo; but will you be determin'd by a whole Church?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Now you come cloſe, could you but find a whole Church owning this.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I think 'tis no hard matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>What Church, and where I pray?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>The Church of <hi>England,</hi> and in this very Article you have now read, and that in theſe words,—<hi>There is but one living and true God,—Maker and Preſerver of all things.</hi> Now how will you grant God to be the Preſerver of all things to this very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and not allow of Providence?—And to aſſure you this is her meaning, the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of our Church are anſwerable to her faith, <hi>v. Coll.</hi> for the 8th Sunday after <hi>Trin, Whoſe never failing Providence,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Preſerver! I profeſs 'tis ſo, <hi>Preſerver</hi> and <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver failing Providence!</hi> I never minded it before. This has ſomewhat in it to your purpoſe more than I have noted.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Something in't! for ſhame <hi>Tim,</hi> knock under: what, ſubſcribe ſuch an Article as this, and to the uſe of ſuch a prayer as this, and yet deny Providence? Muſt God preſerve the world, and yet not be at the leaſt concerned in any thing done in the world? O non-ſenſe! ſtupidity! the very <hi>Heathens</hi> ſpoke more like Divines and Chriſtians than you, and the reſt of your Atheiſtical gang. Hear what one of them ſaith (and he none of the beſt neither), <hi>Seneca</hi> I mean, who calleth God, the <hi>Keeper and Governour of the whole world; a mind, a ſpirit, the Lord and Artificer</hi> (or Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator of all the world), <hi>he to whom every name agreeth. Will you call him fate? You will not be out; for he it is on whom all things depend. Will you call him Providence? You will
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94521:4"/>ſay right; for by his counſel the world is provided, and taken care for, that it remains ſteady,
<note place="margin">Cuſtodem, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorem<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſi, animum &amp; ſpiritum, mundani hu jus operis Do minum &amp; Artificem, cui nomen omne convenit. Vis illum fatum vocare? Non errabis. Hic eſt, ex quo ſuſpenſa ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omnia, cauſa cauſarum. Vis illum Providentiam dicere? Recte dices. Eſt enim cujus conſilio huic mundo provide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ut in inconcuſſus eat, &amp; actus ſuos explicet, <hi>Sen. Nat. Qu. l.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 45.</note> and performeth its operations</hi>—Thus he. And <hi>Du-pleſſis,</hi> Lord of <hi>Morney,</hi> in his Book of the trueneſs of Chriſtian Religion, <hi>ch.</hi> 13. ſheweth, that Providence is abundantly own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Plato, Plotinus, Hierocles, Ariſtotle, Cicero</hi> and others. And in ſhort, none but ſome of the moſt ſenſual and brutiſh <hi>Epicureans,</hi> ever ſo much as called this in queſtion.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>And ſuppoſe they do, What ill conſequence can follow upon it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Many and ſad ones, tho' perhaps otherwiſe in your opinion; for firſt, you hereby deny God's Mercy, Wiſdom and Goodneſs, in that you ſuppoſe him to take no care at all of, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the numberleſs number of creatures that he hath made. Next, you abridge him of his Soveraignty, and take his Prerogative from him, which is this, To diſpenſe good and evil as he pleaſeth; <hi>Is there evil in the City and I have not done it, ſaith the Lord?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Amos,</note> Nay, you do in effect deny his being, and ungod him, to ſuppoſe him to ſit like an old man, idle in Heaven, and unconcerned at what is done here below. Another ſad conſequence is, that all the ſigns in Heaven, Comets, Blazing-ſtars, all heavy and ſore Judgments upon Kingdoms in general, as War, Plague, Fire, Famine, ſignifie no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; with all perſonal calamity and afflictions:
<note place="margin">Pompin.</note> And that all good as well as evil comes by chance and fortune; that God hath no hand or providence in the diſpenſation of either, Conſequently all ground and reaſon of Thankfulneſs or Humiliation towards God vaniſheth, ſince her is not to be owned either in the good we receive, or the the evil that we ſuffer— What think you of theſe things?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe are ſad indeed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet true and natural Inferences from your Doctrine; and if you would ſpeak out, you muſt own it: As a Divine of our Church once did, when being exhorted by a Perſon of Quality to give God thanks for his good Providence in raiſing him to ſuch a Preſerment, replied to this purpoſe, <hi>Providence!</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thank my Money and my Friends, for without theſe I had gone without it, for all Providence.</hi> Are not theſe truſty Lads to their Subſcriptions of the Articles!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Enough of this, Sir, I have done: Let us go on to the next.—</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="article">
               <head>Artic. 2.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Son, which is the Word of the Father, begotten from everlaſting of the Father, the very and Eternal God, of one ſubſtance with the Father, took mans nature in the Womb of the bleſſed Virgin, of her ſubſtance; ſo that two whole and perfect Natures, that is to ſay, the Godhead and Manhood, were joyned together in one perſon never to be divided; whereof is one Chriſt, very God and very man, who truly ſuffered, was crucified, dead and buried, to reconcile his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to us, and to be a ſacrifice not only for Original guilt, but alſo for actual ſins of men.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>This is another Article you and I have ſubſcribed to, and profeſs to own, and have promiſed to maintain.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>And good reaſon; for I ſee nothing in it but what is ſound and Orthodox; and he deſerves not the name of a Chriſtian that ſays otherwiſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I am of your mind; yet I fear you have cracked ſome part of it in your elaborate diſcourſes <hi>ex tempore.</hi> To try you, I will only crave your Opinion of one little branch of it; What think you of <hi>Original Sin?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I take it to be only a privation of Original Righteouſneſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Now I know whereabouts you are; You are one of thoſe ſubtil Gentlemen, who ſubſcribe the Articles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and when you have done, preach the Doctrines of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and Canons of the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi> This is very pretty! a Popiſh Prieſt may do as much.
<note place="margin">Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> Seſſ, 3. Can. 6.</note> But we will debate farther on this in its proper place, under <hi>Artic.</hi> 9. which ſpeaks as plain Engliſh in this point, as ever Article did.—Go on therefore to the next.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="article">
               <head>Artic. 3.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As Chriſt died for us, and was buried: ſo alſo it is to be believed, that he went down into Hell.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Here is ſomething in this Article will take up a little more of our time than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, becauſe it is a matter of weight, and what I know you and I much differ in?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>What can that be? 'tis all mighty plain to me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>No doubt, ſince you never read it before; but when you have conſidered it as oft and throughly as I have done, perhaps you may heſitate as well as I, in what ſenſe we are to take the latter part of it, viz. <hi>So alſo it is to be believed, that he went down into Hell.</hi> Pray what is your ſenſe of it? and how do you teach people to underſtand it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>That Chriſt did perſonally and locally go down into Hell, that is, into the place or ſtate of the damned, to ſuffer there; to conquer and overcome the Devils in their place of reſidency, and to free thoſe Souls that were detained in Hell till Chriſt's deſcenſion thither.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> know ſome of the Ancients, and all the Papiſts are of this opinion; yet I confeſs 'tis not clear to me, nor do I find any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to think our Church intends this ſenſe in her Article. And if you will have patience with me, I ſhall give you my Reaſons for it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I will exerciſe what patience I can; but pray be brief.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>As brief as the weight of the matter will give me leave. To explain the Terms of the Article a little [<hi>He went down, or deſcended</hi>]: To deſcend, is properly to to go down by bodily motion from an higher place to a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94521:5"/>lower: But in a borrowed ſenſe, or ſpeech, it ſignifies a change of ſtate, from better to worſe, from great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to meaner, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 47.1. <hi>Come down</hi> (or deſcend), <hi>and ſit in the duſt, O virgin daughter of Babylon [into Hell]:</hi> The word here <hi>Engliſhed Hell,</hi> in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> is <hi>Sheol,</hi> in <hi>Greek</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: And this I find is taken four ways in Scripture; For the grave, or place of the dead, 1 <hi>King</hi> 2.6. For the power of death, or ſtate of the dead, appointed to all men, good and bad, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.48. For extreme humiliation or abaſement, or ſuch ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and pains as may be compared to helliſh ſufferings, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.5. and for the place and ſtate of the damned, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.23. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and when he was in Hell Now in which of theſe ſenſes do you take it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>In the laſt, as without doubt our Church intends it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>That is, not in any, or all the three firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> the grave, the power of death, or extreme abaſement and helliſh ſufferings, but in the laſt, namely, that Chriſt deſcended into the place of the damned, ſuffered in the ſame flames wherein the rich man cries out he was tormented, and wherein the Devils themſelves and damned Spirits have ſuffered, do and ſhall ſuffer for ever.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, I believe ſo, and ſhall never believe otherwiſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Perhaps you may, when you have heard what I have to ofter to the contrary, which now follows: 1. It is not clearly recorded (as all other parts of our Belief are) in Holy Scripture, that Chriſt did locally and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally deſcend into the place and ſtate of the damned: For the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> taken in this ſenſe, occurs but once in all the New Teſtament, <hi>viz. Luk.</hi> 16.23. which is not ſpoken of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> but of <hi>Dives.</hi> Nor doth the word there ſignifie the place of the damned, from the force or propriety of it, but from the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances which are there noted: For <hi>Dives</hi> is not ſimply ſaid to be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>in inferno, ſeu Gebenna,</hi> but in torments and flames. Moreover the Evangeliſts, who have profeſſedly delivered to us the whole Hiſtory of our Saviour, from his Incarnation to his Aſcenſion, have not made the leaſt mention of his deſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into Hell in this ſenſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Surely you are miſtaken.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Diſcover where; And I cannot conceive they would have omitted it, had Chriſt done it or had it been neceſſary to ſalvation to believe it: Particularly, St. <hi>Luke</hi> writes nothing of it in his Goſpel; in his Preface to which, he tells <hi>Theophilus,</hi> That he would write to him in order of all thoſe things where of he had perfect underſtanding, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.3. And St. <hi>Paul,</hi> rehearſing certain chief Heads which he had preached to his <hi>Corinthians,</hi> mentions the Death, Burial and Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Chriſt, but not his local deſcenſion to the ſtate and place of the damned (which had been a fit place and opportunity to have inſerted it); yet affirms, he had preached what would ſuffice to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, if they were not wanting to themſelves, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.1, to 5.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>You begin to ſhake me, when I thought I had been invincibly ſetled, and unconquerable: you give me ſoft words, but hard Arguments; have you any more behind? for I think long till this combat is ended?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, 2. I ſay further, that if Chriſt deſcended to the place or ſeat of the damned, it was either in <hi>his ſoul,</hi> which the Scripture teſtifies went the day (or moment of his Death) into Paradiſe, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.43. a place of Joy, not torment; and in the ſame Chapter he ſaith himſelf. He commended his ſoul into the hand of his father, in the ſame ſenſe no doubt, that St. <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> did after his example. Or elſe <hi>in his Body,</hi> which we are aſſured by the ſame Infallible Spirit, was in the grave till the third day, the day of his Reſurrection, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.40. Or elſe <hi>in his Godhead;</hi> but to attribute deſcenſion to the Godhead is improper, which is in all places at one and the ſame time; nor is the Godhead ſubject to paſſion. How then did he deſcend?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, I cannot par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularize them, but ſurely it was neceſſary he ſhould do ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Doubtleſs then it was done, for Chriſt omitted nothing neceſſary to be done or ſuffered, in order to the great redemption he was ſent to accompliſh. But as the Scripture doth not clearly affirm it, ſo to me it ſeems not of abſolute neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, in order to our redemption, that our ſurety ſhould deſcend to the place of the damned, and ſuffer there.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>What are your reaſons for this opinion?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe the place of ſuffering is but a circumſtance. Hell, the place of the damned, is no part of the debt Chriſt was to pay; nor ſuffering there locally, any part of payment, that we read of in the Goſpel. As the ſurety may ſatisfie the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor in any place appointed for payment, or in open Court; which being done, the debtor and ſurety are both acquitted, and need not go to Priſon: If they be caſt into Priſon, 'tis becauſe they do not pay the debt; for all that Juſtice requires, is the payment of the debt, to which the Priſon is meerly extrinſecal. So the Juſtice of God cannot be ſatisfied for the tranſgreſſion of his law, but by the death of the ſinner. Now it doth not require, that this be done, or this ſatisfaction be made in Priſon, or in the place of the damned; for the wicked go thither becauſe they cannot pay the debt, or make ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But our ſurety, Jeſus Chriſt, who undertook the debt for us, hath made ſuch full ſatisfaction on the Croſs, that himſelf ſaid, juſt before he gave up the Ghoſt, <hi>Conſummatum eſt,</hi> the work was finiſhed. And the Apoſtles ſo underſtood Chriſt, which made them aſcribe all to his ſuffering, or to the merit of his ſufferings on the Croſs, as ſpoiling of <hi>principalities and powers;</hi> by which is meant the power of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Devils, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.15. <hi>and the blotting out the hand-writing that was againſt us, Col.</hi> 2.14. our reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to God, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.20 and tell us, that he is able now to <hi>render us unblameable and unreproveable in the ſight of God,</hi> Col 22. <hi>Having by that offering of himſelf, for ever perfected them that are ſanctified,</hi> Heb. 10.14. And if God is ſatisfied, Mans Redemption perfected, and Believers perfected by his Death, I can ſee no neceſſity of the following deſcenſion into Hell.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>This is all very rational and convincing. But what makes you think that our Church doth not underſtand it of a local deſcenſion, and require the belief of it as neceſſary to Salvation?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Two things have raiſed in me ſuch an opinion, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. Becauſe ſhe doth not here (nor any where elſe that I can find) give any ſuch ſenſe, or interpretation of the words; which were a very dangerous omiſſion, if the belief of it were neceſſary to ſalvation.—And 2. Becauſe in her 8th Article, where ſhe mentions the 3. Creeds, which ſhe affirms agreeable to Scripture, <hi>viz.</hi> the Apoſtles, the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> and <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed (which ſhe not only allows, but enjoyns the uſe of in her Liturgy or publick Service), hath in the laſt of theſe left the <hi>deſcention of Chriſt into Hell</hi> wholly out, which ſhe certainly would not have omitted, but have inſerted it here as well as in the <hi>Athanaſian,</hi> had ſhe thought the belief of it neceſſary to ſalvation, or deſigned to bind us to the belief of it; for this were to render that Creed imperfect, which ſhe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows as perfect, and according to Scripture.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:94521:5"/>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Really my Stomach begins to turn at a local deſcention; yet ere you can work a full Converſion, you muſt Anſwer an Objection or two, which I have ſwimming in my Noddle, againſt what you have ſaid.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Out with them, <hi>Tim.</hi> and I'le do the beſt I can to cleanſe thy Stomach and Head too; the latter being (I fear) as much oppreſſed with ill Notions, as the former is with ill Humours.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>My firſt Objection is this, <hi>The Terrours and Torments which Chriſt Suffered in his Soul upon the Croſs, went before his Burial, but his deſcention into Hell follows it in our Creed and Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle: therefore his deſcention in Hell concerns not theſe Torments.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Cunningly offered; this diſcovers thee either Knave or Fool in <hi>Logick,</hi> which you like beſt: for the Minor of this Syllogiſm is faulty; alledging, <hi>Non Cauſa pro Cauſa:</hi> or that for a Cauſe which is none. For know,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In the Creed, our Saviours Deſcention into Hell is put after his Burial, as an Illuſtration of what went before touching his Sufferings or Paſſion, leaſt any thing ſhould be detracted from it; and not that it was performed after it. As if it had been ſaid, He not only ſuffered in Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Dyed, and was laid in the Grave, but alſo ſuffered extream Tortures, Helliſh Torments in his Soul too, ſuch as made him cry-out on the Croſs, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. And if you obſerve it, <hi>(Tim.)</hi> you will find all along in the Creed, a Proceſſion in the Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Lord, from a leſſer to a greater Suffering: from the grief and pains of his Body, to thoſe of his Soul. That he did ſuffer in his Soul greatly, himſelf Affirms, and we all believe. Now where in all the Creed can you find any thing that may expreſs his Soul-ſufferings, if not theſe Words, <hi>He deſcended into Hell? He ſuffered under Pontius Pilate, was Crucified, dead and buried,</hi> is all: which all might be, and he ſuffer in his body only; and this the Thieves ſuffered, which were Crucified with him. But his <hi>Deſcending into Hell,</hi> implys ſomewhat more, <hi>viz.</hi> Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in his Soul: which is all the Judicious and Learned <hi>Hamon</hi> ſaith on that Text,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ham.</hi> Act. 2.27.</note> 
                     <hi>Thou wilt. not leave my Soul in Hell.</hi> And it is therefore put laſt, or mentioned after his Death and Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial, to ſhew, that it was the greateſt and ſharpeſt part of Chriſts Sufferings.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Moreover, for the order of expreſſing it, I meet with the very ſame, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.23. <hi>The rich man dyed and was buried, and when he was in Hell, &amp;c.</hi> No doubt his <hi>Soul</hi> was in <hi>Hell</hi> before his <hi>Body</hi> was in the <hi>Grave;</hi> and yet his Burial is put firſt by our Saviour, and his Soul-ſufferings afterwards, as being onely a higher and farther degree of Miſery.—So in the Creed it is ſaid, (or in the Article) Chriſt was Dead, Buried, and deſcended into Hell; or ſuffered in his Soul Helliſh Torments, as the ſenſe of Gods Wrath, the loſs of Gods ſight and preſence for a time, due for our Sins:—Not that his Death was before his Sufferings in his Soul, but theſe are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned laſt, as being the greateſt, far greater than the Death of the Body: and the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Chriſts Paſſion and Humiliation. And to Conclude otherwiſe, as that Chriſt could not, or did not ſuffer in his Soul theſe Helliſh Torments before his Death or Burial, becauſe mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned after both; is all one as if you ſhould infer, that never any went to Hell before they were Buried; becauſe it is ſaid in that fore-mentioned Text, That <hi>the Rich man Died, was Buried, and when he was in Hell, &amp;c.</hi> which were a groſs Error, and contrary to Scripture. Nay, then it will follow, that the Soul cannot go to Hell, ſo long as the Body remains unburied: an inference ſo abſurd, that a man of any Reaſon or Religion, will neither make nor own it.—What ſay you <hi>Tim.</hi> are we over this ſtile?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Pretty well, Thanks to you for the good lift you gave me; but there is another yet behind, as hard to clamber as the former, at which I doubt we ſhall both ſtick.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Never fear it, man, I'le heave with both hands, but I'le have you over, now we are come thus far: What is it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seeing theſe words</hi> [He Deſcended into Hell] <hi>are ſo dubious, and have cauſed ſuch a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, why are they not wholly left out of our Articles and Creed?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſee you were more afraid than hurt; for your frightful <hi>Objection</hi> is dwindled into a little <hi>Queſtion:</hi> this Bar is ſo low, you may almoſt go over without help, were you not ſo very weak. However, that I may not leave you behind, know firſt, that every thing that is a Controverſie, is not an Hereſie, either in matter of Doctrine or Faith, and therefore not preſently to be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punged out of our Creed. And ſince it hath been received by the Church in all Ages (ſince the Fourth Century, as <hi>Bellarm.</hi> tells us) and being rightly underſtood, contains in it a truth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to godlineſs, yea neceſſary to be believed unto Salvation, as the Sufferings of Chriſt in his Soul, and continuing in the ſtate of the Dead for a time. I ſay, it being ſo antient, and (right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) underſtood ſo neceſſary, we may not leave it out; but retain it to the Edification of our Faith, and Conſolation of our Souls.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> If becauſe there hath been ſome difference or diſpute about the meaning of this Phraſe in our Creed or Articles, we ſhould preſently abandon it, by the ſame Rule we muſt expunge many Texts of Scripture out of our Bible: as, thoſe that concern the Doctrine of <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Reprobation, Free-will, Falling away from Grace, &amp;c.</hi> Controverted by Learned men on both ſides, and of different Perſwaſions. This is no Rule for putting out of the Articles of our Faith therefore, barely becauſe Controverſies have riſen about the meaning and ſenſe of it. But I have been too prolix already, therefore let us diſmiſs this Point.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:94521:6"/>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>No, I am ſo well ſatisfied, that I muſt entreat you to give me the Sum of what you ſaid, as brief as you can; for my Memory is very ſhort: and I would fain retain ſomewhat, if Poſſible.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>The ſhort then is this, There are I ſay theſe two different ſenſes of theſe words, <hi>He Deſcended into Hell.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Which is the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſome of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients, and all the</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</note> Some thereby underſtand literally a Local Deſcenſion into the Place or State of the Damned, to conquer the Devils, and ſo ſet free thoſe Souls, that were kept in Hell, till Chriſts Deſcenſion. Others underſtand no more than a further degree of Humiliation, then his Death and Burial. Namely, the continuing under the Power of Death for a time: or of the Sufferings in his Soul on the Croſs; whereon our Bleſſed Saviour was humbled <hi>uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad Inferni tremenda tormenta,</hi> or endured for a time thoſe Torments, <hi>Quae reprobi in aeternum ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuri ſunt,</hi> Which the wicked ſhall Eternally ſuffer in Hell. As the loſs of the ſenſe of Gods favour,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>This is the Opinion of ſome Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and moſt of our Modern Reformed fines</hi>
                     </note> the Malediction or Wrath of God in his Soul, which is Hell, or that Fire which ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be quenched; In which, Chriſt himſelf for a time was ſcorched for our Sins. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may truly enough be ſaid, To Deſcend into Hell. Theſe, Brother <hi>Tim.</hi> are the two ſenſes; which of theſe now do you apprehend the moſt agreeable to Scripture and the Analogy of Faith?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>The latter clearly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Then we have done with this, your ſatisfaction being all I aim at in this Diſcourſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>No, there is one little Queſtion more comes into my mind, though I queſtion whether you can Anſwer it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>It may be not: for you know the Proverb,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>But let's hear it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why did not our Biſhops, when by His Majeſties Command at his firſt Return, they inſpected the</hi> Common-Prayer, <hi>and Corrected ſome things in it, put ſome gloſs upon theſe words in the Creed, that we might not have been in the Dark, as to their ſenſe of them, which now we are?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>It had been very eaſie for them to have done it, and why 'twas omitted, I can give no reaſon, unleſs it was either becauſe we ſhould not know their Opinion, or becauſe (it may be) they were divided in their Opinions about it. Or elſe, that they would not aſſume the Honour of doing all that was needful to be done of this Nature, but leave ſome things to their Succeſſors; among which, this may be one. And in the next Edition, or next Generation (God grant the Liturgy and Biſhops to ſtand till then) you may expect it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis well Reply'd, I will inquire no further. Let us proceed.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="article">
               <head>Article IV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt did truly riſe again from Death, and took again his body, with Fleſh, Bones, and all things appertaining to the perfection of Mans Nature, wherewith he Aſcended into Heaven, and there ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, until he return to Judge all men at the Laſt Day.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>The principal intents of this Article are the Reſurrection, Aſcenſion of our Saviour, with his Coming to Judgment; in either of which, I confeſs I cannot charge you, nor I hope any one elſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>No, I am ſure they cannot, the People to whom I have Preached now Two Sundays toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, can bear me Witneſs I am found here, for I have handled theſe main Doctrines amongſt them; though I never knew they were part of the Articles of the Church before.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>That's not material to you, whether you Preach according to the Articles you have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed or not. But by the way, I obſerve</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>you have a Whisking Faculty at handling, to handle Three ſuch Points in two half hours or thereabouts.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, I was not longer, yet performed ſo well, that I had as many thankful ſcrapes, as Dr. <hi>O.</hi> himſelf for his long interwoven Diſcourſe of late, at—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis like you might have as many Tongues, but I doubt not ſo many Guineys, as he.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Guineys, what are they?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Now I ſee thou art ignorant of ſomething beſides the Articles: Guineys they are the great Procurers of Advouſons, Preſentations, and Eccleſiaſtical Preferments; their Principal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence is about the Court, and they ſometimes help a Church-man at a dead lift, when Merits and Friends both fail.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I wiſh I could meet with one of theſe Courteous Gentlemen, I am ſure none ever ſtood in more need of his Aſſiſtance.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>One? no leſs than ſome hundreds, (according as the Place may be Thouſands) will do you any kindneſs at all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, then I deſpair, for having lived Forty years and never met with one, 'tis more than probable I ſhall be dead before I procure a Thouſand to ſtand my Friends.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>It will do you more good to underſtand the Articles of the Church, and practiſe them; for that will make you happier in Forty years more, than all the Guineys in <hi>England</hi> can. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore puſh on to the next.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="article">
               <head>Article V.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Holy Ghoſt, proceeding from the Father and the Son, is of one Subſtance, Majeſty and Glory, with the Father and the Son, very and eternal God.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:94521:6"/>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Here I hope you are found too.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes truly, for the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed teacheth me thus much touching the Holy Ghoſt; which Creed I have often Repeated, and do moſt ſtedfaſtly believe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I wiſh all that have ſubſcribed this Article could ſay as much.—But let us have the Sixth.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="article">
               <head>Article VI.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Holy Scripture containeth all things neceſſary to Salvation: ſo that whatſoever is not read therein, nor may be proved thereby, is not to be required of any man, that it ſhould be believed as an Article of the Faith, or be thought requiſite or neceſſary to Salvation. In the name of the Holy Scripture, we do underſtand thoſe Canonical Books of the Old and New Teſtament, of whoſe autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity was never any doubt in the Church.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>As to this, I hope, you are perfectly Orthodox.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>So perfectly, that I wiſh all but the Canonical Books of Scripture, had been left out of our Calendar; for ſince our Church here Affirms that theſe Contain all <hi>things neceſſary to Salvation, and conſequently are ſufficient, for Example of Life, and inſtruction of Manners,</hi> I think we might have made a pretty good ſhift with theſe (eſpecially on Sundays) without <hi>Tobias, Bell and the Dragon,</hi> with the uſe of the <hi>Apocraphites.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>And I Aſſure you, if our Calendar were to ſuffer a new impreſſion, and I were the Corrector, I ſhould not boggle much to gratifie you in this Opinion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I thank you for your good will: but ſince it is not in my power, nor yours to amend it, we muſt be content, and make as much uſe of the former, and as little of the latter, as poſſibly we may.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Very good, I wiſh we agree in the next as well as we do in this.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="article">
               <head>Article VII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Old Teſtament is not Contrary to the New, for both in the Old and New Teſtament, ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life is offered to mankind by Chriſt, who is the only Mediator between God and Man, being both God and Man. Wherefore they are not to be heard, which feign that the old Fathers did look only for tranſitory promiſes. Although the Law given from God by Moſes, as touching Ceremonies and Rites, do not bind Chriſtian men, nor the civil Precepts thereof ought of neceſſity to be received in any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Wealth: Yet notwithſtanding, no Chriſtian man whatſoever is free from the obedience of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments which are called Moral.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>This Article hath a great Deal in it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Where lies it, I don't perceive it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>No? Why it Requires of every Chriſtian Man Obedience to all the Commands called Moral; now how do you Comport with it in your Practice?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I own it, Obedience is Due to all the Commands that are Moral?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Why is there any that is not Moral?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, I think ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Which is that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>The Fourth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſo? Don't the Article term it ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I can't tell, I don't believe it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Nor a great many beſides you, who have ſubſcribed this Article, yet deny the ſence of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I muſt be plain, In troth I hold it no more moral than All Saints, or the Fifth of <hi>November.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I thought ſomewhat was the matter, you make ſo ſlight of it;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Why doth the Church require all her Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, when this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand is read to ſay Lord have mercy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us and incline our hearts to keep this Law, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> that you can ſhare one half of it Weekly to your own uſe and Service.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>And I hope no Offence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>And as you give your People leave in the Afternoon, ſo many of them take leave for the Forenoon; and thus you ſhare the whole betwixt you, leaving the reſt to God Almighty,—Yet no Offence I hope.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>If it be Moral, why is it not perpetuall without Alteration?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis the ſhameful Prophanation of this Day, by you and ſuch as have Sucked in your Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, that hath Uſhered in ſo much Irreligion amongſt us, and helped to pull down ſuch ſevere Judgments upon us. But hoping, being better informed, you will become reformed, hear me a little, as to this point.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>When you have ſaid all you can, you can never prove it Moral and perpetual.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>You have owned 'tis ſo, by your Subſcription of this Article, and will you now queſtion it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, I do, for I knew not there was any ſuch Article amongſt them, if I had known it I—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay never Repent you have done it, for you have no cauſe, if you underſtood as you ought.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Underſtand what?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:94521:7"/>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>That the Morality of this Fourth Command lies not in obſerving, the Seventh day from the Creation: for the Fourth Commandment doth not require to uſe and ſanctifie the Seventh Day from the Creation, not from any other period or Date of time, but only the Seventh Day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Six of Labour, or coming between Six of Labour in a ſettled Courſe of Numbring from any Period that God ſhould appoint, and ſo in the Meaning of that Commandment, we do now and ever muſt uſe the Seventh Day. For the Seventh is that part in order of Numbering, which ſtill comes between Six, having Six before it and Six after it continually, and ſo our <hi>Sunday,</hi> our Day of reſt hath, and therefore we alſo reſt the Seventh Day.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I deny it, ours is the firſt, not the Seventh.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>And the Seventh as much as the firſt; the firſt of our Week, and Seventh after Six of Labour. Indeed the Period from which we take the beginning of our Account is not the ſame, but another from the <hi>Jews;</hi> for they did Reckon from the beginning of the Creation and ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, we from the Reſurrection and ſo forward; but ours is as truely and ſurely the Seventh, as theirs, though Reckoned from another Period: and as for the Period whence the account muſt be made, we have no word at all in the Precept. For the Precept ſaith, not Six Days from the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation thou ſhalt labour, and the Seventh from the Creation is the Sabbath of the Lord; but, <hi>Six Days ſhalt thou labour;</hi> nor doth it ſay, <hi>The Lord bleſſed and Sanctified the Seventh Day from the Creation,</hi> but the <hi>Sabbath Day,</hi> that is, the Seventh after Six of labour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>And what do you underſtand by all this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I underſtand, what I ſuppoſe the Article Enjoynes, <hi>by Requiring every Chriſtian to yield obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Commandments,</hi> and ſo to this Fourth among the reſt <hi>viz.</hi> That you and I, and every Chriſtian, is oblidg'd by vertue of this Command for ever, to reſt every Seventh day after Six from all labour, Recreation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to Dedicate it in Solemn manner, wholly to the worſhip and Service of God, by preaching, Reading, Praying, and other Holy Religious Duties and Exerciſes both in Publick and Private. Conſider this a little, and give me your thoughts.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I need not much time to Study, I have (in the Company I have been Converſant with, ſome Clergy men as well as others) heard the Sabbath ſo Decryed, and the ſtrickt Obſervation of it ſo ſlighted and vilified, that I thought there was little in it, more than another day. But for the future, I hope I ſhall be more diligent in preparing for it, and more ſtrickt and ſerious in the Obſervation of it, than ever I have been.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>You will do very well, and to endeavour to bring it into greater eſteem and veneration with the people, wherever you come, for the life of all Religion amongſt us, conſiſts in a due keeping this day; and believe it our own practice in this regard, will prevail more than our Preaching, Inaſmuch as Examples are of more force with men than Precepts. And 'tis our Obedience to Gods Commands, which muſt evidence the ſincerity of our Faith, contained in the Creeds mentioned in the next Article.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="article">
               <head>Article VIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The three Creeds,</hi> Nice <hi>Creed,</hi> Athanaſius <hi>Creed, and that which is commonly called the</hi> Apoſtles <hi>Creed, ought throughly to be received, and believed: for they may be proved by moſt certain war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants of Holy Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Touching this, I think I need not queſtion you: for though you never ſee them in the Articles before, yet you have often Read them in the Common-Prayer; and I ſuppoſe with hearty aſſent to the Articles of Chriſtian Faith contained in them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I do ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Let us therefore hear the next, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="article">
               <head>Article IX.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Original Sin ſtandeth not in the following of</hi> Adam (<hi>as the</hi> Pelagians <hi>do vainly talk) but it is the fault and corruption of the nature of every man, that naturally is ingendred of the off-ſpring of</hi> Adam, <hi>whereby man is very far gone from Original Righteouſneſs, and is of his own Nature in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to evil; ſo that the fleſh luſteth always contrary to the Spirit: and therefore in every perſon born into this world, it deſerveth Gods wrath and damnation. And this infection of Nature doth remain, yea, in them that are regenerated, whereby the luſt of the Fleſh, called in Greek, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which ſome do expound the wiſdom, ſome ſenſuality, ſome the affection, ſome the deſire of the fleſh, is not ſubject to the Law od. And although there is no condemnation for them that Believe and are Baptized, yet the Apoſtle doth confeſs, that concupiſence and luſt hath of it ſelf the nature of ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>If I remember right, at Reading the ſecond Article, you diſcovered your ſelf a little infirm and faulty, about Original ſin, calling it only a privation of Original Righteouſneſs, what think you now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:94521:7"/>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I think if I had Read this Article, I ſhould never have Subſcribed it, nor do I believe it now I have Subſcribed it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>What nothing, no part of it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Truely very little, a very ſmall part of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Do you believe the Scriptures? if you do, I ſee no reaſon why we ſhould not believe this found Article of our Church, even every ſhred and Syllable of it. For,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It aſſerts that there is Original ſin; which is called <hi>ſin,</hi> Rom. 7.8. <hi>The ſining ſin.</hi> Rom. 7.13. <hi>The ſin that dwelleth in us.</hi> Rom. 7, 20. <hi>The ſin that ſo eaſily beſets us,</hi> Heb. 11.1. <hi>The body of ſin. The body of Death. The Law in the Members.</hi> It is alſo called <hi>Feſh.
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.23.24. Joh. 3.6. Rom. 7.5. Ro. 7.25. King. 1.8.38. Heb. 12. Jam. 1.14.</note> The old man. The Law of ſin. The plague in ones own heart. And the root of bitterneſs.</hi> Beſides the woful effects we find of it in our ſelves, proves it. As blindneſs in the mind, darkneſs in underſtanding, rebellion in the will, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with unholy and unclean affections, proneneſs to ſinful, and averſneſs to Holy and Godly Actions.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Next this Article teacheth us, that this <hi>Original corruption remains in every man, even in the Regenerate:</hi> and this St. <hi>Paul</hi> acknowledgeth at large in <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17. He ſaith the Fleſh luſteth againſt, the Spirit, ſo that we cannot do the things we would. And St. <hi>James,</hi> Every man is tempted when he is drawn away of his own Luſt. And the beſt of Gods Children bewail the remainder and indwelling of this Luſt and Corruption: doubtleſs therefore our Church is right thus far.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. And alſo in ſaying, [<hi>in every perſon born into the world deſerves Hell and Damnation</hi>] for if it be ſin, as hath been proved already, it can deſerve no leſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.5.6. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.15.
<note place="margin">Ro. 6.23.</note> So that I can find nothing in this Article but may go down very well, if <hi>Arminius</hi> or <hi>Socinus</hi> hath not turned your Stomach againſt it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>It can never enter into my Head, that <hi>Adams</hi> ſin, he being but one, ſhould defile the Univerſal Nature.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I thought <hi>Socinus</hi> was in your Belly before, now he looks out at your mouth.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.47. Ro. 5.12.17.</note> 
                     <hi>Adam</hi> had in him the whole Nature of mankind, and by his one offence the whole Nature was defiled.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Adams</hi> ſin was not voluntary in us, we never gave gave conſent to it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>There is a twofold will, <hi>Voluntas Nature,</hi> the whole Nature of man was repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in <hi>Adam,</hi> therefore the will of Nature was ſufficient to convey the ſin Nature, <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent as Perſonae,</hi> and by every actual ſin, we juſtifie <hi>Adams</hi> breach of Covenant, and that Text <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12, 19. ſeems clear for the imputation of <hi>Adams</hi> ſin. All were in <hi>Adam,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Peccatum Adami ita poſterii imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ac ſi omnes i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traniſſent.</hi> Bellarm. Again. <hi>Peccatum Originale, tametſi ab Adamo eſt non tamen Adami, ſed noſtrum eſt.</hi> Tom. 4. l. 4. c. 3. &amp; 8.</note> and ſinned (in him) <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and ſo our laſt Tranſlation in the Margin. Though it be rendered [for that all have ſinned] yet muſt it be underſtood [in him, or ſinned in <hi>Adam</hi>] elſe it is not true, that all upon whom death hath paſſed have ſinned, as namely Infants newly born. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis not ſaid all are ſinners, but all have ſinned, which imports an imputation of <hi>Adams,</hi> act unto his Poſterity. So that without queſtion you and I are as guilty of this ſin, as if we had been preſent and joyned with <hi>Adam</hi> in it. And the offering of another <hi>Adam</hi> to thee and me in the Church, ſhews that the diſpenſation of God is not rigorous, for we may ſhare in his obedience, as well as in the others diſobedience. It is as agreeable to the Wiſdom and Juſtice of God by the ſin of the Firſt <hi>Adam</hi> to entail death upon all his Children, as to the Wiſdom and Grace of God by the Obedience and Righteouſneſs of the Second <hi>Adam,</hi> to confer Life upon his Children. Have I ſaid any thing towards your Conviction?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, a great deal, but to little purpoſe, for I don't underſtand this putative ſin, and putative Righteouſneſs of the Firſt and Second <hi>Adam.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Take heed [<hi>Tim.</hi>] of making a mock of theſe ſerious matters: I could tell where you learned that word [putative] for a need. But as merry as you and your Companions make your ſelves with it, know that if imputative Righteouſneſs don't juſtifie you, you are in a worſe condition than the Scribes and Phariſees, whoſe Righteouſneſs Legal, I am afraid exceeded yours, and yet inſufficient to carry them to Heaven, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.20. And St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who was as to the Law blameleſs, doth yet deſire not to be found in his own Righteouſneſs, but that which is by Faith through Chriſt Jeſus, the Righteouſneſs (putative as you in deriſion term it) which is in God by Faith, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9. But of this in a more proper place. I only demand this of you [<hi>Tim.</hi>] that though you plaid the fool in ſubſcribing this Article before you Read it; yet that you would not play the Knave in diſowning it, now you have Subſcribed it, making a mock of it: for you muſt needs underſtand it, if you underſtand <hi>Engliſh,</hi> for never any thing ſaid more plainly that there is Original ſin in all, remaining in the beſt of men, and that <hi>Adams</hi> ſin is ſo far ours, as we deſerve Hell and Damnation for it. And aſſure your ſelf, unleſs (after this war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) I hear you are Reformed as to this matter, I ſhall acquaint the Biſhop what a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriber and maintainer you are of the Articles of our Church, who I doubt not will call you to an account. For I ſtedfaſtly believe his Lordſhip holds it a leſs ſin to be defective in the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, than in the Articles: and will ſooner Suſpend for the latter, than the former. But I hope you will give me no cauſe—eſpecially when you have Read the next.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="article">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:94521:8"/>
               <head>Article X.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The condition of man after the fall of</hi> Adam, <hi>is ſuch, That he cannot turn and prepare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by his own natural ſtrength and good works, to faith and calling upon God: Wherefore we have no power to do good works pleaſant and acceptable to God, without the Grace of God by Chriſt preventing us, that we may have a good will, and working with us when we have that good will.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>The following Article Concords ſo well with this, that 'tis pitty to part them; if you will, therefore, Read that too, before we proceed farther.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="article">
               <head>Article XI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>We are accounted Righteous before God, only for the merit of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt by Faith, and not for our own works, or deſervings. Wherefore that we are Juſtified by Faith only, is a moſt wholſome Doctrine, and very full of comfort, as more largely is expreſſed in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of Juſtification.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>As to theſe two Articles, I need not ask your Opinion, for I know you to be as rotten in theſe, as an Egg nine days ſat on. <hi>Free Will</hi> and the neceſſity and efficacy of Works to Juſtifie without putative Righteouſneſs, is ſo much your tone in the Pulpit, that the very Bells in the Steeple have learned the Tune. And when you are approaching the Church, the leaſt jar out of it puts you into ſuch an Arminian chafe, that the Bells are preſently forſooth <hi>Calviniſtical</hi> Bells, the Ringers <hi>Calviniſtical</hi> Rogues, wiſhing the Ropes in their hands faſt about their Necks. An admirable Devotion at your firſt entrance into Gods Houſe!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>And there are more of this Opinion beſides my ſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>What Opinion? That the Ninth, Tenth, and Eleventh Chapters to the <hi>Romans,</hi> were foiſted into that Epiſtle by <hi>Calvin,</hi> or at leaſt he had an hand in Compoſing our Articles?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>No neither, but for <hi>Free Will,</hi> and Juſtification without putative Righteouſneſs; that Chriſt came chiefly to be an Example to us, and not to Juſtifie us by the imputation of his Righteouſneſs, this is the Opinion I know many are of beſides me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Aye, too many: but for you and I, and thoſe men you mean, who have conſented and Subſcribed to theſe Articles, to talk at this rate, I muſt tell you, is a fault not to be born with; whatever others ſay, that are free, we that are obliged by Promiſes and Subſcriptions, ſhould be honeſt and true to them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Honeſt and True? Yes ſo I ought, but I have learned better ſince my Subſcription; and I hope you will give a man leave to improve his Reaſon and Underſtanding?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes by all means, but ſuppoſe you were called to Subſcribe theſe very Articles word for word again, now your Reaſon is ſo mightily improved, what would you do?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>A needleſs queſtion, for that's not likely.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Why not? Put caſe the Patron of a Good (that is a great) Living, or about two hundred or three hundred pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> ſhould out of his Generoſity freely offer you the Preſentation to it: would you refuſe his kindneſs, rather than Subſcratch for it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I am afraid I ſhould ſcarce withſtand the force of ſo taking a temptation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>And you would Read them openly in the Pariſh Church, the people being preſent, and openly declare your approbation of them, and full conſent to them (as the Law requires) ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than loſe ſuch a Benefice?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I believe I ſhould, I wiſh ſome body would try me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>And Preach and Prate againſt them, or contrary to them, when you had done, ha!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Not directly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Directly or indirectly, directly you would be a Knave for your pains; not to ſay worſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>You would not have me talk contrary to what I believe, would you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>What is that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I believe every man hath a power and freedom of Will to good Works as well as Evil.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>What Naturally, and in an unregenerate Eſtate?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:94521:8"/>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>This is contrary to the Tenth Article, as Aye and No, directly Oppoſite to Scripture, <hi>Which ſaith, the Carnal mind is enmity againſt God, for it is not ſubject to the Law of God; nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed can be: ſo then, they that are in the Fleſh cannot pleaſe God. The Natural Man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God; for they are fooliſhneſs unto him: neither can he know them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are Spiritualy diſcerned. No man can ſay, Jeſus is the Lord, but by the Holy Ghoſt. Not that we are ſufficient of our ſelves to think any thing as of our ſelves, but our ſufficiency is of God. And without me ye can do nothing, ſaith our Saviour.</hi> Repugnant is your belief alſo to many Prayers of our Church. <hi>As the Collect for the Second Sunday in Lent. The Fifth Sunday after Eaſter. The Ninth Sunday after Trinity. The Seventeenth Sunday after Trinity. The Nineteenth, The Collect on All-Saints Day,</hi> and many more. Now what a rare Believer are you, to believe contrary to the Word of God, the Articles you have Subſcribed,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7.8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.3. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. <hi>John</hi> 15.5.</note> and the Prayers you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly make uſe of, and are obliged to put up to God on thoſe ſeveral days, in the preſcribed Words and no other. But what's the next part of your Belief in this matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>That as I have a Power and freedom of will to <hi>Good Works,</hi> ſo I muſt do them, in order to my being Juſtified before God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>This is as Corrupt and Erroneous as the former, and as oppoſite to the next Article, read it.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="article">
               <head>Article XII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Albeit, that</hi> Good Works, <hi>which are the fruits of Faith, and follow after juſtification, cannot put away our Sins, and endure the ſeverity of Gods Judgment, yet are they pleaſing and acceptable to God in Chriſt, and do ſpring out neceſſarily of a true and lively Faith, inſomuch that by them a lively Faith may be as evidently known, as a tree diſcerned by the Fruit.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Here you are Taught, That <hi>Good Works</hi> are pleaſing and acceptable to God; but ſo far are they from juſtifying without Faith, that they are the fruits of Faith, and follow after Juſtification. Plainly implying, That we muſt have true Faith, and be juſtified, before we can do any <hi>Works,</hi> good, pleaſing or acceptable to God. So that I believe (according to our Church) that Faith in Chriſt juſtifies the Perſon, and <hi>Good Works</hi> the Faith: Or thus, I take it, that God juſtifies Judicially, Chriſt Jeſus Meritoriouſly, Faith Inſtrumentally, and Good Works Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>So then, you will make <hi>Good Works</hi> of little worth; and it matters not whether a man hath them or not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>No ſuch matter, I believe they are abſolutely neceſſary to Salvation; that no man can go to Heaven without them; for they are (as this <hi>Twelfth Article tells you) the genuine and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fruits of a true and lively Faith;</hi> and that there can be no ſuch Faith without them. And St. <hi>James</hi> ſaith as much in the Second Chapter of his Epiſtle at large. I believe that Text of Holy Writ, which tells me, <hi>Without Holineſs no man ſhall ſee the Lord,</hi> with an equal Faith,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14 <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6.</note> that I do that which ſaith, <hi>Without Faith 'tis impoſſible to pleaſe God.</hi> That is, that both are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to make a good Chriſtian, and there is no other, I am ſure, ſhall ever enter into Heaven. And to cloſe this Diſcourſe, I believe, he that Teaches ſuch Doctrine as this, ſtands further off from <hi>Rome,</hi> comes nearer to the Analogy of Faith, the Tenour of the Holy Goſpel, and the ſound Articles of our Church, then thoſe Men who Teach or Preach otherwiſe: and I hope by this time you think ſo too.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I am inclinable to ſuch thoughts.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>And the more you think on't, the more inclinable you will ſtill be, if you do not wilfully ſhut your Eyes againſt the Light of Gods Word, and of the following Articles, grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="article">
               <head>Article XIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Works done before the grace of Christ, and the Inſpiration of his Spirit, are not pleaſant to God, foraſmuch as they ſpring not of Faith in Jeſu Chriſt, neither do they make men meet to receive Grace, or (as the School Authors ſay) deſerve Grace of congruity: yea, rather for that they are not done as God hath willed and commanded them to be done, we doubt not but they have the nature of Sin.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>What think you of this added to all the reſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>It ſtill helps to Confirm what you have ſaid, and to convince me of my Errour, without any farther Comment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Proceed then to the next, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="article">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:94521:9"/>
               <head>Article XIV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Voluntary works beſides, over and above Gods Commandments, which they call Works of Superero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, cannot be taught without Arrogancy and Impiety. For by them Men do declare, that they do not only render unto God as much as they are bound to do, but that they do more for his ſake, then of boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den duty is required: Whereas Chriſt ſaith plainly, When ye have done all that are Commanded to you, ſay, We are unprofitable Servants.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I have ſuch Charity for thee <hi>(Tim.)</hi> as not to think thee ſo far <hi>Popefied,</hi> as to oppoſe this Article.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>You may, for ſurely we who neither do, nor can do all that God Commands, have lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ground to boaſt of doing more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Honeſtly ſaid, <hi>Tim.</hi> I hope to find thee right as to the next too.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="article">
               <head>Article XV.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt in the truth of our Nature, was made like unto us in all things (Sin only except) from which he was clearly void, both in his fleſh, and in Spirit. He came to be a Lamb without ſpot, who by ſacrifice of himſelf once made, ſhould take away the Sins of the World: and ſin (as St.</hi> John <hi>ſaith) was not in him. But all we the reſt (although Baptized, and born again in Chriſt) yet offend in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, and if we ſay we have no Sin, we deceive our ſelves, and the Truth is not in us.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I know nothing contained in this Article, that you do Oppoſe or Cavil at: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore think the beſt, never loving to make quarrels, when there is not juſt and apparent Cauſe for it. Therefore let us view the following one.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="article">
               <head>Article XVI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Not every deadly Sin willingly committed after Baptiſm, is Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable. Wherefore the grant of Repentance is not to be denyed to ſuch as fall into Sin after Baptiſm. After we have received the Holy Ghoſt, we may depart from grace given, and fall into Sin, and by the grace of God (we may) ariſe again, and amend our lives. And therefore they are to be Condemned, which ſay, they can no more Sin as long as they live here, to deny the place of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs to ſuch as truly Repent.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>What think you of this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Sound and good.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis ſo, if underſtood aright: but by a Sermon you lately Preached at St. <hi>B</hi>'s. Church; I preſume, you miſtake one Clauſe of it vilely, either willfully or ignorantly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Which is that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis in theſe Words, <hi>after we have received the Holy Ghoſt, we may depart from Grace given, and fall into Sin.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Miſtake the ſenſe of the Article in this, 'tis not eaſie, nay, 'tis almoſt impoſſible to miſs it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, what is the ſenſe, ſay you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>That Believers, or ſuch as have received the Spirit of God, and his ſaving Graces, may fall away.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>What totally and finally, and periſh Everlaſtingly?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, totally and finally, and be Damned.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I judged I ſhould find you as ſound in this Point, as that Sheep, that ſhaking her ſelf in a froſty Morning, falls in pieces. That this Article (or our Church in it) doth not intend a total and final Apoſtacy, is apparent to me, by theſe Two things.</p>
               </sp>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe ſhe ſaith not, That ſuch as have received the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may fall away; but that <hi>they may fall into Sin,</hi> as <hi>David, Peter</hi> and others, who Sinned or fell into great and groſs Sins after Grace given, yet no final Apoſtates.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe ſhe ſaith in this Article, <hi>That the grant of Repentance is not to be denyed</hi> to ſuch; as it is to be granted, They which thus Sin, after the Reception of the Holy Ghoſt, and Grace given, may Repent; <hi>And by the Grace of God may riſe again, and amend their Lives,</hi> as the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Saints and Servants of God, <hi>David,</hi> and St. <hi>Peter</hi> did: which no final, total Apoſtate ever did, or can do. Therefore, it cannot be meant of a final Apoſtacy, or <hi>falling away from Grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:94521:9"/>
               <p> And therefore if you have taught any ſuch Doctrine, you have Preached down this Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, and many plain Texts of Scripture to boot, as <hi>They ſhould deceive (if it were poſſible) the very Elect. Whom he loveth, he loveth to the end. The gifts and calling of God are without Repentance. Kept by the power of God through Faith, unto Salvation.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30.</note> He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth in him ſhall not be confounded. Whom he did predeſtinate, them he alſo called, whom he called, them he alſo juſtified, whom he juſtified, them he alſo glorified.</hi> And many more gracious and infallible promiſes, aſſuring us of the ſtability, and perſeverance of true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, of ſuch as have received the Holy Ghoſt, and Graces thereof.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, now we are in indeed, if we are come to Election and Predeſtination.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, and good and proper mediums too, to prove no final apoſtacy, or falling away from grace; for grant the one, and the other follows. Election and Predeſtination are inconſiſtent with a total and final defection. But I hope [<hi>Tim</hi>] theſe are not frightfull terms to you, you have heard of them before?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, but don't well underſtand them, Election and Predeſtination! 'tis nonſenſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Such ſenſe as you have ſubſcribed to, and conſequently ſhould believe, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain againſt all Arminians and other Oppoſers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I can't imagin any Article of our Church aſſerts any ſuch thing, ſo contrary to all reaſon, as nothing can be more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, this is ſuch an unreaſonable Article, and by good luck the very next in courſe, and ſo full mouth'd for Election and Predeſtination, that you'ld think ſome body ſpoke it through <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Mouth, or at leaſt that: that wretched, ſtiff Predeſtinarian gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the hand of him that writ it.—Look there, 'tis [<hi>Tim.</hi>] nay, ne'er ſtart at it: but out with it, like a man of metal.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="article">
               <head>Article 17.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Predeſtination to life is the Everlaſting purpoſe of God, whereby (before the Foundations of the World were laid) he hath conſtantly decreed by his Counſel, ſecret to us, to deliver from curſe and damnation thoſe whom he hath choſen in Chriſt out of Mankind; and to bring them by Chriſt to Everlaſting Salvation, as Veſſels made to Honour: wherefore they which be endued with ſo excellent a benefit of God, be called according to Gods purpoſe by his Spirit, working in due ſeaſon; they through Grace obey the calling, they be juſtified freely, they be made Sons of God by Adoption, they be made like the Image of his only begotten Son Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, they walk Religiouſly in good works: and at length by Gods mercy, they attain to Everlaſting Felicity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As the Godly conſideration of Predeſtination, and our Election in Chriſt is full of ſweet, pleaſant and unſpeakable comfort to Godly Perſons, and ſuch as feel in themſelves the working of the Spirit of Chriſt. mortifying the works of the Fleſh, and their Earthly Members, and drawing up their mind to high and Heavenly things, as well becauſe it doth greatly eſtabliſh and confirm their Faith of Eternal Salvation, to be enjoyed through Chriſt, as becauſe it doth fervently kindle their love towards God: So, for curious and carnal perſons, lacking the Spirit of Chriſt, to have continually before their eyes the ſentence of Gods predeſtination, is a moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous downfall, whereby the Devil doth thruſt them either into deſperation, or into wretchleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of moſt unclean living, no leſs perillous than deſperation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Furthermore, we muſt receive Gods promiſes in ſuch wife as they be generally ſet forth to us in Holy Scripture: and in our doings, that will of God is to be followed, which we have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly declared unto us in the word of God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Bleſs me, what's the reaſon of this ſudden paleneſs in your countenance? you look as though you were fainting away.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Not ſo Sir, but I am ſtricken with a ſtrange horror and aſtoniſhment, to think how our Pulpits ring of Doctrines directly contrary to this Article; for though I was ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs as never to read the Articles till now, yet I concluded theſe great Dons had, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver queſtioning their honeſty, I was confirmed in it, by their conſtant preaching, no ſuch Article could poſſibly be: but now I ſee they are out as much as I, I pity them with all my heart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Pity thy ſelf man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I do ſo, but them more, becauſe I declare it, mine was a ſin of Ignorance, I am afraid theirs is otherwiſe: and becauſe, being leading men, they have drawn me and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more into this error, by their authority.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I am more than half of your opinion. For our Church (as fore-ſeeing how prone men would be to dance after <hi>Arminius</hi> his Pipe) hath taken more pains in framing this Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle than ordinary, on purpoſe to prevent them; and 'tis ſo full, ſo plain and punctual,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94521:10"/>that (one would think) no miſtake can ariſe, but what is willfull.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Full and punctual? there is all that ever can be thought on againſt Univerſal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, Free Will, Falling away from Grace, and the uſe of thoſe points, which are moſt what their ſubjects, eſpecially on popular occaſions.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Take the contents of the Article, and you will be confirmed in your opinion— which are theſe,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. There is a predeſtination of Men unto Everlaſting Life.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Predeſtination hath been from Everlaſting.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Not all men, but certain, are Predeſtinated to be ſaved.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. They which are Predeſtinate unto Salvation, cannot periſh.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. In Chriſt Jeſus, of the meer will and purpoſe of God ſome are Elected, and not others to Salvation.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. They who are Elected unto Salvation, if they come unto years of diſcretion, are called both, outwardly by the word, and inwardly by the Spirit of God.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. The Predeſtinate are both juſtified by Faith, ſanctified by the Holy Ghoſt, and ſhall be glorified in the life to come.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. The conſideration of Predeſtination is to the Godly moſt comfortable, but to curious and carnal perſons very dangerous.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. The general promiſes of God, ſet forth in Holy Scripture, are to be embraced of us.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. In our actions the word of God, which is his revealed will, muſt be our direction. Theſe are the ſeveral Doctrines laid down and aſſerted in this Article.—Would you have any more?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>No, here is enough, and as much as all, that ever wrote for Predeſtination and Election, can ſay: and had our Church enlarged this Article to the bulk of the Common Prayer, ſhe could not have ſpoke more to the purpoſe, than ſhe hath in this one Page. I wonder the Reverend Fathers of the Church will ſuffer her Sons to wrong her, as they do dayly, openly making her ſpeak through their Mouths, and often through the louder mouth of the preſs, thoſe Tenets, which ſhe never held, nay, which in the very body of her Articles, ſhe ſo plainly diſowns and contradicts.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I rejoyce at your Conviction: Now theſe being fundamental points, it may not be amiſs, (I think) nor time ill ſpent, to ſee a little (for your fuller ſatisfaction and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation) what ground and footing each point in this Article hath in holy writ; the perfect Rule and Touchſtone of all matters of Faith, and manners.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>No ſure, no loſs of time, but time well improved; and if you will take ſo much pains, I ſhall thankfully partake of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>For the vindication of our Church, reprehenſion of thoſe men who have ſubſcribed to her, and yet oppoſe her, and for thy eſtabliſhment <hi>(Tim.)</hi> I will do it. To begin with the firſt then.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>There is a Predeſtination of men unto life Everlaſting.</hi> To fit on my Right hand, and on my left,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 20.23. <hi>Math.</hi> 22.14. <hi>Math.</hi> 24.23. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.37.</note> is not <hi>mine</hi> to give, but ſhall be given to them, for whom it is <hi>prepared</hi> of my <hi>Father.</hi> For many are called but few <hi>choſen.</hi> But for the <hi>Elects</hi> ſake thoſe dayes ſhall be ſhortned. All that the Father hath <hi>given</hi> me ſhall come unto me. To this truth alſo doe the Evangeliſts St. <hi>Luke</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> give witneſs: the former faith that of the Gentiles at <hi>Antioch,</hi> ſo many as were <hi>Ordained</hi> unto Eternal life <hi>believed:</hi> and the other ſaith, whom he foreknew he alſo did <hi>Predeſtinate.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 13.48. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29.</note> And <hi>Paul</hi> bleſſeth God for this, ſaying, Bleſſed be God the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who, &amp;c. hath <hi>choſen us in him, before the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the world;
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.3, 4, 5.</note> having Predeſtinated us unto the adoption of Children by Jeſus Chriſt unto himſelf.</hi> Are not theſe Texts to the purpoſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>As clear as can be.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Beſides the Example of the Elected Creatures, Men and Angels; of the two brethren <hi>Abel</hi> and <hi>Cain; Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael; Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau;</hi> of the two ſervants of King <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> of the two Kingdoms of <hi>Juda</hi> and <hi>Iſrael;</hi> the two peoples <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles:</hi> the two A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Judas;</hi> the two thieves upon the Croſs; the two men in the fields; the women at the Mill, are a great illuſtration to this truth.—The next is,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Predeſtination hath been from Everlaſting,</hi> or before all times; Then ſhall the King ſay unto them on his right hand, come ye bleſſed of my father: inherit the <hi>Kingdom prepared</hi> for you from the <hi>foundation of the world:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 25 34.</note> which the Apoſtle underſtands to be from Everlaſting, ſaying God hath choſen us in him before <hi>the foundation of the world.</hi> Again, God hath ſaved us and called us with an holy calling, not <hi>accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our works,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.4.</note> but according to his own <hi>purpoſe and grace,</hi> which was given us in Chriſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94521:10"/>Jeſus, <hi>before the world began.</hi>—And as good footing on the ſame word hath the following point, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Not all men, but certain, are predeſtinated to be ſaved.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 10.20. Joh. 16.14 2 Tim. 2.10</note> Rejoyce that <hi>your names</hi> are written in heaven, ſaith our Saviour, and I know <hi>mine,</hi> and am known of <hi>mine.</hi> I ſuffer all things for the <hi>Elects ſake.</hi> And our Church (in her order for burial of the dead) prayes for the accompliſhment of the <hi>number of Gods Elect.</hi> And again in the ſame Office, come yea bleſſed, receive the Kingdom prepared <hi>for you.</hi> And in the form of Baptiſm, we pray that the infant (to be baptized) may remain in the number of <hi>thine Elect Children, &amp;c.</hi> not all men, but a certain number are Elected or Predeſtinated to life.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>They which are Predeſtinated unto Salvation cannot periſh.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joh. 6.37.</note> All that the Father hath given me, <hi>ſhall come unto me,</hi> and him that cometh to me, I will in no wiſe caſt out. I give unto them eternal life, and they ſhall <hi>never periſh,</hi> neither ſhall any man pluck them out of my hand; and no man is able to pluck them out of my Fathers hand,
<note place="margin">Joh. 10.28, 29. Math. 16.18. Rom. 8 30. Rom. 11.29.</note> who is greater than all. And the gates of hell ſhall not prevail againſt them. Moreover, whom he Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, them he alſo glorified. The gifts and calling of God are without repentance. They went out from us, becauſe they were not of us; for if they had been of us, they would have continued with us.—So the next point (which theſe men ſo much ſtick at) is as cleerly taught in Gods word, as any of the former,—namely</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>That of the meer will and purpoſe of God, ſome men in Chriſt Jeſus are Elected, and not others, unto ſalvation.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>a</hi> Rom. 9.11. <hi>b</hi> Eph 1.5. <hi>c</hi> 2 Tim. 1.9. <hi>d</hi> Exod. 33.19. <hi>e</hi> Rom. 9.15. <hi>f</hi> Eph. 1.4, 5. <hi>g</hi> 1 Pet. 1.18, 19, 20. <hi>h</hi> Eph. 1.5, 6. Prov. 16.4. Rom. 9.21.</note> 
                     <hi>a</hi> That the purpoſe of God according to Election might ſtand. <hi>b</hi> Having Predſtinated us according to the good pleaſure of his will. <hi>c</hi> Not according to our works, but according to his own purpoſe and grace. <hi>d</hi> I will have mercy on whom I will have mercy, &amp;c. <hi>f</hi> He hath choſen us in Chriſt, and Predeſtinated us through Chriſt. <hi>g</hi> Ye are not redeemed with corruptible things, &amp;c. but by the precious blood of Chriſt, as of a Lamb, &amp;c. who verily was <hi>foreordained,</hi> before the foundation of the world, but was manifeſt in theſe laſt times <hi>for you.</hi> Who hath Predeſtinated us to the praiſe of the glory of his grace. The Lord hath made all things for himſelf, yea even the wicked for the day of wrath. Hath not the Potter power over the clay, of the ſame lump to make one veſſel unto honour, another unto diſhonour?—was ever any thing more fully and plainly ſaid in holy writ, than this part of our Article?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I think not, or can be.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe portions of Scripture (to which more might be added were it needfull) doe not barely aſſert a Predeſtination of ſome, and not of others, but aſſign alſo all the cauſes of ſuch Predeſtination,—as</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Cauſe efficient, to be the everlaſting purpoſe of God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Cauſe formal, Gods infinite goodneſs, mercy and free grace.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Cauſe material, the blood of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Cauſe final or end, (why both God the Father hath loved, and Chriſt for his Elect hath ſuffered) is the glory of God and the ſalvation of men: ſo that I cannot ſee how any man, who is at enmity with this Article, can hold any good friendſhip with theſe Texts of Scripture: or with thoſe that ariſe to prove the next point, which is this,</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>They, who are Elected unto ſalvation, if they come unto years of diſcretion, are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led both outwardly by the word, and inwardly by the ſpirit of God.</hi> Theſe things are moſt evident and clear in the Scriptures, where is ſet down, both the calling of the Predeſtinate, their obedience to the word being called,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.30. Gal. 1.15. 1 Theſſ. 2.12. 2 Tim. 1.9. Eph. 1.13.</note> their adoption by the Spirit to be the chidren of God, and their holineſs of life and converſation,—whom he did Predeſtinate, them he alſo <hi>called.</hi> God ſeparated me from my mothers womb, <hi>Called me</hi> by his grace. Walk wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of God, who hath <hi>Called you</hi> to his Kingdom and glory. He hath ſaved us and <hi>called us with an holy calling,</hi> according to his own purpoſe and grace, &amp;c. In whom alſo ye truſted, after ye heard the word of truth, the goſpel of your ſalvation. Ye have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the ſpirit of adoption, whereby we cry, Abba father,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.15, 16.</note> the ſame ſpirit bearing wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with your ſpirits, that we are the children of God.
<note place="margin">Eph. 2.10.</note> And for their being choſen and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to holineſs of life and good works, the Apoſtle plainly enough aſſerts, ſaying we are his workmanſhip, created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works, which God hath ordained that we ſhould walk in them. And the Grace of God hath appeared,
<note place="margin">Tit. 2.11.12.</note> &amp;c. teaching us that deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, we ſhould live ſoberly, righteouſly and Godly in this preſent world.—yea ſaith the next Propoſition.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. <hi>The Predeſtinate are both juſtified by faith, ſanctified by the Spirit, and ſhall be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in the life to come.</hi> All theſe bleſſed effects of Predeſtination, doth the Scripture fully aſſert, for know (ſaith the Apoſtle) a man is not juſtified by the works of the Law,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94521:11"/>but by the faith of Jeſus Chriſt.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16.</note> Moreover whom he predeſtinated, &amp;c. them he alſo glorified. If children then heirs, heirs of God, and joint-heirs with Chriſt. And as we have born the image of the earthly,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30. <hi>v.</hi> 17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.49.</note> ſo ſhall we bear the image of the heavenly. Now are not all theſe conſequents of Predeſtination, <hi>viz.</hi> Juſtification, Sanctification, and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification fully enough expreſſed in theſe Texts?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Very fully, in my opinion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Therefore very well doth our Church ſay, in the next part of this Article, That</p>
                  <p n="8">8. <hi>The conſideration of Predeſtination, is to the godly moſt comfortable; but to curious and carnal perſons very dangerous.</hi> To the former, the Meditation of it muſt needs be exceeding ſweet, pleaſant and comfortable, becauſe it greatly confirms their faith in Chriſt, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes their love towards God.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18. <hi>v.</hi> 31, 32, 33, 34.</note> I account the ſufferings of this preſent time, are not worthy to be compared with the glory, that ſhall be revealed in us. If God be for us, who can be againſt us? He that ſpared not his own Son, how ſhall he not, with him, freely give us all things. Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods Elect, it is God that juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, who is he that condemneth? ye are ſealed with the holy ſpirit of promiſe, which is the earneſt of our inheritance,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13, 14.</note> until the redemption of the purchaſed poſſeſſion, unto the praiſe of his glory. And again, grieve not the holy Spirit whereby ye are ſealed unto the day of Redemption.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.30.</note> Here is a deep and large Well of Conſolation to the godly; yet not affording the leſt drop to carnal and wicked men.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>But doth not this Doctrine lead towards Deſperation?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>by no means; for no man, either from the word of God, or this Article of our Church, can gather, that he is a veſſel of wrath fitted for deſtruction; but contrariwiſe, by many and great arguments may perſwade himſelf, that God wills not his deſtruction, as by the next propoſition plainly appears, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9. <hi>That the general promiſes of God, ſet forth in holy Scripture, are to be embraced of us,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 11.38.39. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16.17. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4.</note> ſuch are, <hi>Come unto me all ye that travel and are heavy laden, and I will give you reſt.</hi> God gave his onely beloved Son, that whoſoever believeth in him, ſhould not periſh, &amp;c. Who will have all men to be ſaved and come to the knowledge of the truth. Theſe and many more ſuch general Promiſes of grace and favour to mankind are heartily to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced of us, as encouragements to faith, repentance and an holy life. So that whoever embraceth theſe promiſes, (and as our Church in the cloſe of this Article ſaith.)</p>
                  <p n="10">10. <hi>Will in his actions be directed by the revealed will of God, hath no ground to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire, or to exclude himſelf out of the number of Gods Predeſtinate or choſen ones.</hi> Thus you ſee the drift of this Article, comprehending moſt fully and clearly, that great doctrine of Predeſtination, with all its coherent doctrines, which is ſo much cryed down in our day; and (which is the wonder and ſhame of all) by ſome ſons of our Church, who have ſubſcribed it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I muſt confeſs I have been one of thoſe, led by the example of the greater ones, rather than by the depth of my own knowledge. But ſurely theſe men have ſomething to ſay for themſelves; is not our Church ſingle in this point.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Admit ſhe were, yet there are two weighty reaſons, why they ſhould not deſert or oppoſe her in this: Firſt, Becauſe ſhe hath the Scripture on her ſide; And Secondly, Becauſe they have liſted themſelves her faithfull votaries, by ſubſcription.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>That is true, theſe are plaguy ſtrong tyes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>But withall I ſay, ſhe is not ſingle in this point, for the Churches in, <hi>Helvetia, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil</hi> and <hi>France</hi> believe and hold the ſame, as their publick confeſſions bear witneſs, yea, all the reformed Church.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Who then are the enemies to it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>The <hi>Arminians, Socinians, Antinomians</hi> and <hi>Papiſts;</hi> amongſt theſe laſt, the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits</hi> are the acuteſt and moſt malitious oppoſers of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>This is more than I underſtood before.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>It muſt needs, ſince you never inquired into it before, no, not ſo much as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult the Article, which of it ſelf had been ſufficient to have regulated you, both in your private opinion and publick Doctrine, whereby you have often brought your ſelf under the laſh of that ſevere reprehenſion of St. <hi>Jude,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jude</hi> 10 13.</note> to thoſe, <hi>who foam out their own ſhame, ſpeaking evil of thoſe things, they know not.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I am convinced it had been as well, to have let theſe high points alone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>As well? and much better: had you ſpent your time, and exerciſed your Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent [<hi>Tim</hi>] upon the 10 Commandments; Preached down Atheiſm, Idolatry, Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſs,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94521:11"/>Whoredom, Swearing, and ſuch immoralities; and in Preaching up Faith, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, Sobriety, Righteouſneſs and Godlineſs, you would have done God better ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and had more thanks from your Reverend Dioceſan, than for your yelping againſt Predeſtination, Election, ſtability in grace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without meaſure or reaſon, and (as you acknowledge your ſelf) without underſtanding.—'Tis a miſerable reproach to our Church, to ſee Buzards ſoaring at that, which is above the Eagles flight.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall be more carefull for the time to come; and lay out more hours dayly in Reading than ever I have done.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis well reſolved, and to that forget not to add daily and ſerious praying; and it may not be amiſs to inſert into your private devotions, thoſe requeſts of our Church.— <hi>Lighten our darkneſs, we beſeech thee O Lord, and forgive us all our ſins, negligences and ignorances</hi>—But 'tis time we diſmiſs this, and look to the next Article.—</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="article">
               <head>
                  <hi>Article</hi> 18. Of obtaining eternal Salvation only by the Name of Chriſt.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They alſo are to be had accurſed, that preſume to ſay, that every man ſhall be ſaved by the Law or Sect which he profeſſeth, o that he be diligent to frame his life according to that Law, and the light of nature. For Holy Scripture doth ſet out unto us only the name of Jeſus Chriſt, whereby men muſt be ſaved.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>What is your judgment, touching this Article?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>My judgment is, that our Church is too ſcanty in her charity to damn the greateſt part of the world; even many Heathens, who have lived admirable good, ſtrict and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral lives, according to the Religion, and light they had: and for ought I can ſee, the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs</hi> to boot, and all that lived before Chriſt.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Not a word on't <hi>Tim:</hi> For all that our Church ſaith in this Article is, <hi>That the Profeſſion of every Religion cannot ſave a man, live he never ſo virtuouſly: and that no man ever was or ſhall be ſaved, but only by the name, or Faith of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> This doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> or thoſe before Chriſt, who believed in him to come, and whoſe Faith was every way as beneficial to them, as ours believing in him now he is come, and the Apoſtle recounting many of theſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. ſaith theſe all dyed in the Faith.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>But then what ſhall become of the poor Heathens?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Our Church determines not, but wiſely ſaith, whoſoever among them (or any other fort of Mankind) are ſaved, are ſaved by the name or Faith of Jeſus Chriſt; and no other. And gives you her reaſon, <hi>becauſe the holy Scripture doth ſet it out ſo to us;</hi> ſaying, <hi>through his (Jeſus Chriſts) name, whoſoever believeth in him, ſhall receive remiſſion of ſins:
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 10.43. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.12.</note> neither is there Salvation in any other, for there is none other name under Heaven given among men, whereby we must be ſaved.</hi> So that the charity of our Church in this point, is every whit as large as the Scriptures will allow. And this is the Faith and Confeſſion of the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>(d.) Confeſſ.</hi> Helv. 2. <hi>ar.</hi> 10.11. and 2. <hi>Ch.</hi> 11.13. Baſil. <hi>ar.</hi> 4. Bohem. <hi>c.</hi> 4.10. Gall. <hi>ar.</hi> 13.16, 17. Belg. <hi>ar.</hi> 17.20, 21.</note> and therefore whether your charity [<hi>Tim</hi>] or your ignorance be the greater, I will not ſay; but this I ſay, to ſubſcribe to ſuch a number of unintelligible Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, unſight and unſeen, was no Mathematical demonſtration of a wonderfull wiſdom in you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>But it was a ſign of the greater Faith.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, a Popiſh or implicit Faith, by virtue of which (if the Impoſers honeſty had not been of a better ſtamp than your Faith) you might have under-written to the Alcoran or Maſs-book, as well as the Articles.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>No, hold there.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Why what ſhould have hindered; nay, how do you know you did not; ſince you never lookt what it was?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>But who could divine, but I would?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>That's ſomewhat indeed, for I believe they don't often meet with ſuch blind Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers: which may make them (as you ſay) ſomewhat the more wary. But if the worſt had come to the worſt, you could have come off <hi>tutâ conſcientiâ.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>As you do with the Articles, which you (believe) have ſubſcribed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>How is that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Deny them all, or many (at leaſt) of the moſt conſiderable of them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>What won't go down, muſt come up, and there is an end on't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Then I hope the next will down glibb, for I know nothing in it, that is the leaſt choaky—Try,</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="article">
               <head>
                  <hi>Article</hi> 19. Of the Church.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The viſible Church of Chriſt is a Congregation of faithful men, in the which the pure Word of God is preached, and the Sacraments be duly miniſtred, according to Chriſts ordinance, in all thoſe things that of neceſſity are requiſite to the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:94521:12"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>As the Church of</hi> Hieruſalem, Alexandria <hi>and</hi> Antioch <hi>have erred: So alſo the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>hath erred, not only in their living and manner of Ceremonies, but alſo in matters of Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, are not my words true, there is nothing ſticking here?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, ſomething that ſticks with me a little; and doth not go ſo ſmoothly off, as I expected.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſhould that be; you believe ſuch a thing as a viſible Church of Chriſt, don't you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, but not this deſcription of it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Wherein is it faulty?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>The fault is this, that our Churches charity (in my mind) is as much too great in this, as it is too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in the former Article.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſo, prithee?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe by this deſcription of a true viſible Church, ſhe allowes ſome of the Fanatick Congregations to be true Churches, or at leaſt true members of the viſible Church of Chriſt: for in ſome of theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, <hi>the Word</hi> (they ſay) <hi>is purely preached, and the Sacraments be duly administred, according to Christs Ordinance, in all thoſe things, that of neceſſity are requiſite to the ſame</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>And if it be ſo, why ſhould they not be reckoned among thoſe parts, that help to make up the whole.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>What without the Common Prayer and Ceremonies? theſe true Churches, or true Members of the viſible Church of Chriſt? God deliver me from ſuch Churches.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Why the Article doth not tell you, theſe are neceſſary to the conſtitution of a Church, <hi>but only the Preaching of the pure Word, and right Administration of the Sacraments.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, they are none of our Church, I am ſure.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>True, no more are the Reformed Churches beyond the Seas, yet <hi>parts and members</hi> of the <hi>viſible Church of Chriſt,</hi> and our Church is no more.— But I find <hi>(Tim.)</hi> you have a greater kindneſs for <hi>Socrates, Plato,</hi> and other Heathen, than for theſe Diſſenters, for you could be content, even now, the former might be ſaved, but for the Salvation of theſe latter —</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>What have I to do with their Salvation?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Not much I confeſs; only 'tis an old maxim with Divines, that <hi>Extra Eccleſiam nulla ſalus:</hi> So that if you totally exclude them out of the true Church of Chriſt, you do (as much as in you lyes) to barr them out of Heaven: for which they have reaſon to give you little thanks. —</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I value not their thanks.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>However let them have your Prayers, that ſince they are no Chriſtians as yet, they may be ſuch in time: eſpecially on Good Friday, when you pray <hi>for all Turks, Jews, Infidels and Hereticks,</hi> think on them, will you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Then or not at all, for I know no other part of our Liturgy will comprehend them.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, If I miſtake not, there is one place more, wherein they may be remembred, without much danger of defiling our Prayers with the thoughts of them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Where is that? I cannot call it to mind.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>That's much, when you read it ſome 3 times a week; 'tis that in the Litany — <hi>That it may pleaſe thee to have Mercy upon all men.</hi> So that if you do but allow them to be men (not beaſts) you may venture to let them have a ſhip in that ſentence,—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>You have named all, I am ſure now, wherein they can have any ſhare.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Suppoſe when you read the Confeſſion—<hi>We have left undone thoſe things, which we ought to have done: and we have done thoſe things, which we ought not to have done;</hi> We ſhould underſtand it of the <hi>Phanaticks</hi> as well as of our ſelves, would there be any harm in it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>None in the world, for doubtleſs 'tis true of them to a Tittle. And if there were any more ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, I ſhould begin to think, our Prayers were compoſed chiefly for them: — But ſurely there is no more?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Many more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Where?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>In the Litany, as that—<hi>From all Pride, vain Glory and Hypocriſie; from envy, batred, malice and all uncharitableneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing ever more pertinent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Except that, —<hi>From all Sedition, privy Conſpiracy and Rebellion, from all falſe Doctrine, Hereſie and Schiſme.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Better and better,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And that it may pleaſe thee to bring into the way of Truth, all ſuch as have erred, and are decieved; That it may pleaſe thee to forgive our enemies, perſecutors and ſlanderers, and to turn their hearts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Incomparable I profeſs; I ſhall never read theſe Prayers hence forward, but I ſhall think of the men: they are ſo apt, ſo exceeding apt, that it will add to my devotion ever after, — Where were my Brains that I never noticed this before. As I hope to live, I believe, ſcarce a Biſhop that knew for whoſe ſake, thoſe Prayers were inſerted, till now.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Now then I hope, you will let theſe poor <hi>Gibeonites</hi> ſhare both in your Confeſſions and Petitions, as oft as you may, without turning your Zeal to God, into paſſion againſt them, in Prayer: and I have ſo much Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as to think they will do much for you: and with that ſincerity and love, as becomes fellow members of the viſible Church of Chriſt, for ſuch I take them to be; nor doth our Church in this Article exclude them; which made it ſtick long ſo long by the way, but by this time I hope 'tis pretty well down; if not, I am ſure the next will drive it down.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I'le try.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="article">
               <head>Article 20. Of the Authority of the Church.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Church hath power to decree Rites or Ceremonies, and Authority in Controverſies of Faith: And yet it is not lawfull for the Church to ordain any thing that is contrary to Gods Word written, neither may it ſo expound one place of Scripture, that it be repugnant to another. Wherefore although the Church be a witneſs and a keeper of holy writ, yet as it ought not to decree any thing againſt the ſame, ſo beſides the ſame ought it not to enforce any thing to be believed for neceſſity of ſalvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I need not ask whether you ever read this before, becauſe I know you did not; but how do you like it, now you have read it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:94521:12"/>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Not at all in troth, unleſs by <hi>Church</hi> they mean that at <hi>Weſtminster:</hi> nor can it be true (as to us) in any other ſenſe, for 'tis that <hi>Great Aſſembly</hi> or <hi>General Counoel</hi> that decrees, and appoints all our Rites and Ceremonies, and we have no other than what they approve and eſtabliſh, witneſs the <hi>Act before the Common Prayer.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>But you believe the Church hath a power to decree Rites, which is all the Article aſſerts in that point.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Decree, Ay ſhe may decree and decree till her heart akes, but if ſhe have not the Votes of the Houſe, ſhe ſhall never have the thanks of the Houſe for her pains; and without their Votes and Thanks, I know what her decrees will come to.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>To what?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>To ſcorn and diſdain; with them that make thoſe decrees, 'ſlid man, if all the Reverend Biſhops of the Land ſhould ſit together in Council, and decree a Ceremony no bigger than the daſh over an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, which is ſcarce half a croſs, it would ſignifie no more, than if you and I ſhould do it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>How, you and I, we have no power at all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>En'e as much as their Lordſhips in this caſe, was not the P— but the other day, decreeing out of the Church thoſe Rites and Ceremonies (or a good part of them) that we have; and had it had the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſtamp; the Biſhops might have thrown their Caps after them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>And is it not fit that they which make other Laws, ſhould by Law eſtabliſh the Government in the Church?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Therefore I would have this Article amended, and named thus, the P. (that is King, Lords and Commons Aſſembled, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) have power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Leaving out the Word <hi>Church,</hi> elſe I will never ſubſcribe it;</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>That's done already.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I care not, but I won't own it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>But can you withdraw your hand ſingly from this, and yet ſubſcribe and own the reſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, very well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>That's a cunning trick indeed; 'tis next to a mental reſervation. —By virtue of which, a man may ſubſcribe any thing, all things, and yet in truth ſubſcribe nothing. So that I have all this while been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a miſtake, for I thought you had ſubſcribed all the Articles, and it ſeems you have not, but a little here and there only, as it ſhould pleaſe you, when you come to read them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>And as much too, I think, as reaſon can expect.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Mighty pretty truly; read the next, and (having had your <hi>ſubſcription</hi> before hand) let us now have your <hi>intention,</hi> when you have peruſed it.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="article">
               <head>
                  <hi>Article</hi> 21. Of the Authority of General Councels.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>General Councels may not be gathered together without the Commandment and Will of Princes. And when they be gathered together (foraſmuch as they be an Aſſembly of men whereof all be not governed by the Spirit and Word of God) they may err, and ſometimes have erred, even in things pertaining unto God. Wherefore things ordained by them as neceſſary to ſalvation, have neither ſtrength nor Authority, unleſs it may be declared that they be taken out of holy Scripture.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Now, what did you think of this, at the time of ſubſcription?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>How could I think any thing of what I never ſaw, read nor heard? but now I think 'tis ſound and good, and I own and aſſent to it: though it is like (in our time) there may be no occaſion to make uſe of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Then we'll diſmiſs it to our Succeſſors, and come to the next.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="article">
               <head>
                  <hi>Article</hi> 22. Of Purgatory.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Romiſh Doctrine concerning Purgatory, Pardons, Worſhipping and Adoration, as well of Images, as of Reliques, and alſo Invocation of Saints, is a fond thing, vainly invented, and grounded upon no warranty of Scripture, but rather repugnant to the Word of God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Here I hope your heart ſhall follow your hand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay Sir, and more hearts if I had them, for all this I ſtedfaſtly believe: though I am afraid, this Faith is going out of faſhion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope not; as long as the Defendor of it lives, there is no fear; and if Prayers will add to his days, he is like to live as long as any that ever ſat on his Throne, and therefore I hope our Fears will dye, before he dyes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray God they may, and be buried too, never to riſe more in our Generation, or in the Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons after us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Amen, Amen. —And I am joyful to find you ſo hearty a Proteſtant, I wiſh they be all ſuch, that wear our Livery. —But what's the next Article?</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="article">
               <head>
                  <hi>Article</hi> 23. Of miniſtring in the Congregation.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is not lawful for any man to take upon him the Office of Publick preaching, or miniſtring the Sacraments in the Congregation, before he be lawfully called and ſent to execute the ſame. And thoſe we ought to judge lawfully called and ſent, which be choſen and called to this work by men who have publick authority given unto them in the Congregation, to call and ſend Miniſters into the Lords Vineyard.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſuppoſe we need not ſtay long here neither.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>No, for I know none but <hi>Quakers, Lay-elders,</hi> and ſuch holders forth, as the Apoſtle deſcribes,— That creep into Houſes, and lead captive ſilly women, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but can digeſt this Article well enough, I am ſure there is never an Orthodox Divine (nay, ſcarce a right <hi>Preſbyterian</hi>) but will ſubſcribe to it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Preſbyterian,</hi> yes, for Ordination by laying on of hands is a Doctrine they ſtiffly maintain, both in their Sermons and Writings: yea, and many of them have admitted of Epiſcopal Ordination, rather than run before they were ſent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I know they have, but for all the reſt of the Diſſenters, they had as lieve Old Ketch ſhould goll them as a Biſhop.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then are the <hi>Preſbyterians</hi> decryed as the great bane and peſt in Church and State, when (at leaſt in reſpect to others) they are men of ſome orders. —</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:94521:13"/>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>O Sir, becauſe they are the leading faction.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Leading do you call them, I am ſure they lead the ſmalleſt number, of any Diſſenters this day in the Nation,— yet unhappy men that they are; all that do any ways oppoſe or undermine the Government either in Church or State, are cryed down, under that (new frightfull and abominable) title, <hi>Preſbyterians,</hi> for my part (though I know they are not in infallible yet) I cannot but pity them.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>But I can't, what pity a crew of Knaves and Villains?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Take heed [<hi>Tim.</hi>], for they come neareſt the Church of <hi>England</hi> of any other Diſſenters, and upon a ſmall abatement, could joyn with her, which the reſt of the Diſſenters would not; and are they the worſe Knaves and Villains for this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, much the worſe— but pray ſay no more of them, for I abhor the very name, and cannot hear it repeated with Patience. —</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I would not provoke you too much; but I would gladly hear your reaſons.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>That I can't do without thinking of them, (at leaſt) and the very thoughts of them put me into ſuch an heat, as utterly confounds my reaſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>We uſe to ſay, break my head and ſhew me a reaſon: but it ſeems they muſt be content to be called Knaves, Villains, and what not, without reaſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, for this once they muſt and ſhall; and that for this reaſon, becauſe I can't ſtay now to give my reaſons.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Are they ſo very long then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, much longer I ſee, than the next Article, which I am juſt going to read.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Well [<hi>Tim.</hi>] I perceive 'tis an hard matter to force reaſon from you. — proceed as you will.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="article">
               <head>
                  <hi>Article</hi> 24. Of ſpeaking in the Congregation, in ſuch a Tongue as the people underſtandeth.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is a thing plainly repugnant to the VVord of God, and the cuſtom of the Primitive Church, to have publick Prayer in the Church, or to miniſter the Sacraments in a Tongue not underſtood of the People.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>There is nothing you can diſlike in this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>No, 'tis very Orthodox, and according to the Apoſtles direction. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.6. to 19.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>So, I percieve you have ſome Scripture at command.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, but this Text I cannot but remember: For at one of the conferences appointed by the right Reverend Father in God, the B. of <hi>L.</hi> where the ſubject was againſt Praying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in an unknown tongue; the <hi>Dr.</hi> that Preached in our diviſion, cited this place ſo often, that I ſhall never forget it.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>You give a good account how you came to have it ſo ready at hand— proceed to the next.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="article">
               <head>
                  <hi>Article</hi> 25. Of the Sacraments.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sacraments ordained of Chriſt, be not only badges or tokens of Chriſtian mens profeſſion: but rather they be certain ſure witneſſes, and effectual ſigns of grace, and Gods good will towards us, by the which he doth work inviſibly in us, and doth not onely quicken, but alſo ſtrengthen and confirm our faith in him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>There are two Sacraments ordained of Chriſt our Lord in the Goſpel, that is to ſay Baptiſm and the Supper of the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thoſe five commonly called Sacraments, that is to ſay, Confirmation, Penance, Orders, Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and Extreme <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction, are not to be accounted for Sacraments of the Goſpel, being ſuch as have grown, partly of the corrupt following of the Apoſtles, partly are ſtates of life allowed in the Scriptures; but yet have not like nature of Sacraments with Baptiſm and the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, for that they have not any viſible Sign or Ceremony ordained of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Sacraments were not ordained of Chriſt to be gazed upon, or to be carried about, but that we ſhould duly uſe them. And in ſuch onely as worthily receive the ſame, they have a wholſom effect or operation; but they that receive them unworthily, purchaſe to themſelves damnation, as St.</hi> Paul <hi>ſaith.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>You may read on, for I know not but you'r ſound in this, and I ſhall not charge you, but where I know you are guilty.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="article">
               <head>
                  <hi>Artic.</hi> 26. Of the unworthineſs of the Miniſters, which hinder not the effects of the Sacraments.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Although in the viſible Church the evil be ever mingled with the good, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time the evil have chief authority in the miniſtration of the VVord and Sacraments; yet foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as they do not the ſame in their own name, but in Chriſts, and do miniſter by his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Authority, we may uſe their Miniſtry, both in hearing the VVord of God, and in the receiving of the Sacraments. Neither is the effect of Chriſts Ordinance taken away by their wickedneſs, nor the grace of Gods gifts diminiſhed from ſuch as by faith, and rightly do receive the Saeraments miniſtred unto them, which be effectual, becauſe of Chriſts inſtitution and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, although they be miniſtred by evil men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nevertheleſs, it appertaineth to the Diſcipline of the Church, that enquiry be made of evil Miniſters, and they be accuſed by thoſe that have knowledge of their offences; and finally being found guilty, by juſt judgement be depoſed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>your opinion of this [<hi>Tim?</hi>]</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I have a very good opinion of it, as of any I have yet read.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>But if I miſtake not, there is that in the cloſe of it, toucheth your copy-hold.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>What is that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis this— <hi>nevertheleſs it appertaineth to the Diſcipline of the Church, that enquiry be made of evil Minist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. and that they be accuſed by thoſe that have knowledge of their offneces; and finally, being found guilty, by juſt judgment be depoſed.</hi> Can you heartily conſent to this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:94521:13"/>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, why not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Here is no body preſent but our ſelves, therefore I will be plain with you and tell you the ground of my Queſtion: Were you not long ſince preſented and accuſed to your Dioceſan by the Church wardens of the Pariſh where you offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, there was a Puritanical, Fanatical Church-warden did preſent me, like a ſplenetick Knave as he was.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>But pray what was your Crime?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>A ſmall matter, onely ſitting up too late, and playing the Good-fellow a little too much one Saturday night, being to adminiſter the Sacrament the next morning; and the Raſcal told his Lordſhip 'twas a thing frequent with me ſo to do.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>And what did the Biſhop ſay to you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>He gave me a grave Admonition, and told me, if that wrought not upon me, Suſpenſion ſhould follow.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>He ſpake like himſelf; yet if he had done it, as well as ſaid it, it might have been better; for I don't hear that his Fatherly Admonition hath wrought in you the leaſt reformation. What you did before, I am credibly inform'd you do ſtill: nay, that you mend as ſowr Ale in Summer, inſomuch that the far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of the Pariſh are ſo ſcandalized at you, that they reſolve never to receive the Sacrament at your hands more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis a ſign they are a company of nice, ſqueemiſh Ideots, and know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; elſe they would underſtand that neither my Vices nor my Vertues ſignifie any thing to them in my Preaching the Word, or Adminiſtring the Sacrament.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Then whether you are holy or wicked, ſober or diſorderly in your Life, it muſt be the ſame thing to the People?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, muſt, and is in this Caſe; for doth not this Article ſay, <hi>That he that miniſters doth the ſame not in his own name, but in Chriſts, and by his Commiſſion and Authority—And that the effect of Chriſts Ordinance is not taken away by his</hi> (viz. <hi>the Miniſters) wickedneſs, nor the Grace of Gods Gifts diminiſhed from ſuch as by ſaith do rightly receive the Sacraments miniſtred unto them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>True, theſe are the Words of the Article, and they contain a great Truth: Should a faithleſs wicked man receive the Sacrament at the hands of the holieſt man living, the Holineſs of him that adminiſters would nothing avail ſuch an unworthy Receiver: ſo the contrary. But our Church never intended this as an encouragement to Profaneneſs in her Miniſters, as ſhe plainly declares by the cloſe of the Article; and you make a very ill uſe of it, who ſhall take ſuch liberty from it.—Beſides <hi>(Tim.)</hi> give me leave to tell you, that though the ill living of ſome Miniſters, and their ſlight and irreverent Adminiſtration of the Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, cannot obſtruct the Grace of God towards a worthy Receiver; yet this is a ſhrewd bar to keep off ſober and ſerious Perſons from that Ordinance, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in thoſe Places where they muſt receive from the hands of ſuch Miniſters, or not receive it at all. For what Perſon that hath any ſenſe of God and Religion, and the weight of that ſacred Ordinance upon his mind, (though he ſtrives what he can to conquer all prejudices of this kind) can receive the Elements at the hands of a profligate and irreverent Miniſter, with that ſatisfaction that he can at the hands of one who by his heavenly Life, and exemplary Devotion in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, ſhall excite and quicken the Zeal and Devotion of all that are to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take with him? No, let me diſcharge my Conſcience this once. I heartily wiſh and pray, that thoſe Reverend Fathers who have the Diſcipline of the Church, would narrowly inſpect the Lives and Manners of ſuch Perſons in the Church as you are, who by your diſorderly Converſations, and ſlight, irreverent; and ſlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Adminiſtration of Holy Ordinances, (I muſt tell you without flattery) are a diſhonour to God, a ſcandal to the Goſpel, a reproach to the Miniſtry, the cauſers of Diviſion and Faction, the Promoters of Atheiſm and Profaneneſs, and the bane of all true Godlineſs and Religion. 'Tis you, and ſuch as you, that open the mouths of our Enemies, that turn the glory of our Church into ſhame, and trample her honour in the duſt. 'Tis you, and ſuch as you, that make many ſick and dying ſinners go out of the world without Ghoſtly Counſel and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94521:14"/>Abſolution; the notoriouſneſs of your Crimes raiſing in them a diſguſt againſt you, both living and dying; and who (if any of them miſcarry) muſt anſwer for thoſe Souls?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall not, if they ſend not for me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>But who ſhall anſwer for the cauſe of your not being called at ſuch a time?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>What, you would have Miniſters live like Angels?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Miniſters are called Angels in Scripture; and what if I ſhould ſay they ought to live like Angels, for Purity and Holineſs? I am ſure our Saviour pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds to us an higher Pattern, when he ſaith to his Diſciples, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. laſt. <hi>Be ye perfect, even as your Father which is in Heaven is perfect.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>But that is impoſſible.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>True, as to Equality, but not as to Imitation. St. <hi>Paul</hi> was not equal with our bleſſed Lord for Purity and Holineſs; but he was an imitator of him, as himſelf teſtifies, ſaying, <hi>Be ye followers of me, as I am of Chriſt.</hi> Nor is it impoſſible for you to conſider ſeriouſly the weight and dignity of your Calling, and to take heed thereto,
<note place="margin">Vid. <hi>The Form of Ordering of Prieſts.</hi>
                     </note> as you are exhorted by the Biſhop, at your Ordination; which if you do (as you ought, and there promiſed to do) you ſhall be an able and faithful Miniſter of the Church of Chriſt. The exhortation runs in theſe Words.</p>
               </sp>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> have heard, Brethren, as well in your private Examination, as in the Exhortation which was now made to you, and in the holy Leſſons taken out of the Goſpel, and the Writings of the Apoſtles, of what Dignity, and of how great Importance this Office is, whereunto ye are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. And now again we exhort you in the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that you have in remembrance into how high a Dignity, and to how weighty an Office and Charge ye are called: That is to ſay, to be Meſſengers, Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Stewards of the Lord; to teach and to premoniſh, to feed and provide for the Lords Family; to ſeek for Chriſts Sheep that are diſperſed abroad, and for his Children who are in the midſt of this naughty World, that they may be ſaved through Jeſus Chriſt for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Have always therefore printed in your remembrance, how great a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is committed to your charge, For they are the Sheep of Chriſt, which he bought with his Death, and for whom he ſhed his Blood. The Church and Congregation whom you muſt ſerve, is his Spouſe, and his Body. And if it ſhall happen the ſame Church, òr any Member thereof, to take any hurt or hindrance by reaſon of your negligence, ye know the greatneſs of the fault, and alſo the horrible puniſhment that will enſue. Wherefore conſider with your ſelves the end of your Miniſtry towards the Children of God, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Spouſe and Body of Chriſt; and ſee that you never ceaſe your Labour, your Care, and Diligence, until you have done all that lieth in you, according to your bounden duty, to bring all ſuch as are or ſhall be committed to your Charge, unto that agreement in the Faith and Knowledge of God, and to that ripeneſs and perfectneſs of age in Chriſt, that there be no place left among you, either for Errour in Religion, or for Viciouſneſs in Life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Foraſmuch then as your Office is both of ſo great excellency, and of ſo great difficulty, ye ſee with how great care and ſtudy ye ought to apply your ſelves, as well that ye may ſhew your ſelves dutiful and thankful unto that Lord who hath placed you in ſo high a Dignity; as alſo to beware that neither you your ſelves offend, nor be occaſion that others offend. Howbeit ye cannot have a mind and will thereto of your ſelves; for that will and ability is given of God alone: Therefore ye ought, and have need to pray
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94521:14"/>carneſtly for his holy Spirit. And ſeeing that you cannot by any other means compaſs the doing of ſo weighty a Work, pertaining to the Salvation of Man, but with Doctrine and Exhortation taken out of the holy Scriptures, and with a Life agreeable to the ſame; conſider how ſtudious ye ought to be in reading and learning the Scriptures, and in framing the Manners both of your ſelves, and of them that ſpecially pertain unto you, according to the Rule of the ſame Scriptures: And for this ſelf ſame cauſe, how ye ought to forſake and ſet aſide (as much as you may) all Worldly Cares and Studies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We have good hope that you have well weighed and pondred theſe things with your ſelves long before this time; and that you have clearly determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, by Gods Grace, to give your ſelves wholly to this Office, whereunto it hath pleaſed God to call you: So that as much as lieth in you, you will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply your ſelves wholly to this one thing, and draw all your Cares and Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies this way; and that you will continually pray to God the Father, by the mediation of our only Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, for the heavenly Aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt; that by daily reading and weighing of the Scriptures, ye may wax riper and ſtronger in your Miniſtry, and that ye may ſo endeavour your ſelves from time to time, to ſanctifie the Lives of you and yours, and to faſhion them after the Rule and Doctrine of Chriſt, that ye may be whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom and godly Examples and Patterns for the People to follow.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I confeſs this is very ſerious and weighty, and do acknowledge I never peruſed or pondered it before.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Add to this that daily Prayer at the end of the Confeſſion, <hi>And grant, O moſt merciful Father, for his ſake, that we may hereafter live a godly, righteous and ſober life, to the glory of thy name.</hi> Is not the Miniſter concerned in this, as well as the People, when he ſaith, <hi>and grant that we may, &amp;c?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, without doubt: and by Gods help hereafter my Practice ſhall be more conformable to my Prayers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray God it may, for evil Miniſters ('tis the phraſe uſed in this Article) are moſt odious to God and injurious to his Church, of all others. One ſuch impious Wretch, by his ungodly life, gives ſuch a wound to Religion and the Cauſe of God, as many of his Brethren (though exemplary both in life and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine) are not able to heal. Beſides, I tremble to think of the Reward of ſuch a Miniſter in another world; and what he will be able to plead for himſelf to the great Biſhop of Souls, the Lord Jeſus, at his general and final Viſitation, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.12. I beſeech you therefore <hi>(Tim.)</hi> remember the weight and excellency of your Calling, and the ſolemn Promiſes (in the face of the Congregation) made to God then, when you were admitted to it. Not forgetting your Obligation by Baptiſm, which is the ſubject of the following Article you are next to read.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I give you my hearty thanks, and hope theſe things will make an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon me for good.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall rejoice to ſee it—Go on.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="article">
               <head>ART. 27.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Baptiſm is not only a ſign of Profeſſion, and mark of difference, whereby Chriſtian men are diſcerned from others that be not Chriſtened: but it is alſo a ſign of Regeneration or New Birth, whereby, as by an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they that receive Baptiſm rightly, are grafted into the Church: the Promiſes of the Forgiveneſs of Sin, and of our Adoption to be the Sons of God, by the Holy Ghoſt, are viſibly ſigned and ſealed: Faith is confirmed, and Grace increaſed by vertue of Prayer unto God. The Baptiſm of young Children is in any wiſe to be retained in the Church, as moſt agreeable with the Inſtitution of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:94521:15"/>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſee here what high and noble priviledges are <hi>ſignified and ſealed</hi> to us by our Baptiſm, Regeneration, Adoption, and Remiſſion. To which our Church (explaining this Article in her Catechiſm) adds <hi>Inheritors of the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> What Obligations to an holy Life can there be greater or ſtronger than theſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>None, ſurely.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Add hereto the Covenant on our part, to renounce the Devil and all his Works: to believe the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, and obediently to keep Gods Holy Will and Commandments, and to walk in the ſame all the days of our Lives. Which Covenant, unleſs we perform and keep, we have no right to, or benefit by the aforeſaid Priviledges. Nay, our Baptiſm will prove but an ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation of our Condemnation in the day of Judgment; and an unbaptized Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then would not change eſtates at that day with ſuch a baptized Chriſtian. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, we who are made Miniſters, do moſt ſolemnly devote and dedicate our ſelves to God, to holy ſervices and gaining of ſouls, as the Deputies of Chriſt, in the day that we enter into holy Orders. And if none of all theſe bonds will hold us, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly we are the worſt of men, and deſerve the higheſt Cenſures the Church can inflict upon us. And our Church will never be glorious, till all ſuch Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates be either throughly reformed, or totally ejected out of her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope I do forſake all the Works of the Devil.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Except Drunkenneſs and Swearing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly 'tis very ſeldom: In a paſſion perhaps an Oath may ſlip; and when I meet with good Company I am loath to part, and apt to be merry; but 'tis rare: And bating theſe, I think I have no fellowſhip with the Works of darkneſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>But there is another Vice (I know not whether you will allow it a Work of the Devil or not) you are almoſt incurably infected with, for 'tis Chronical.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>What's that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>That which I think in a Miniſter as bad as either of the former.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I can't imagine what you mean.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I mean Sloth, horrible Sloth and Idleneſs: ſpending little or no time in fitting and improving your ſelf for the difficult and weighty Duties of your Office. And this Vice expoſeth you to the reſt, and all other whatever. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, this makes you ſo profoundly ignorant, that you are not able in any to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable manner to defend our Religion againſt Papiſts and Sectaries; and your weak defence of the Truth confirms them in their Errour, and makes them caſt off all thoughts of reconciliation to our Church. Doubtleſs therefore Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (in a Miniſter) is a great ſin, a woful ſhame, and the Mother of many ſins. And till I ſee you reform this, I ſhall have ſmall hopes of you, as to the reſt— But this is all I ſhall hint to you from this Article, which puts you in mind of your Priviledges and Obligations by your Baptiſm. Now proceed.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="article">
               <head>ART. 28.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Supper of the Lord is not only a ſign of the Love that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ought to have among themſelves one to another; but rather it is a Sacrament of our Redemption by Chriſts Death: Inſomuch that to ſuch as rightly, worthily, and with Faith receive the ſame, the Bread which we break, is a partaking of the Body of Chriſt: and likewiſe the Cup of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, is a partaking of the Blood of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tranſubſtantiation (or the change of the Subſtance of Bread and Wine) in the Supper of the Lord, cannot be proved by Holy Writ: but it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the plain words of Scripture, overthroweth the nature of a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and hath given occaſion to many Superſtitions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Body of Chriſt is given, taken, and eaten in the Supper only after an heavenly and ſpiritual manner. And the mean whereby the Body of Chriſt is received and eaten in the Supper, is Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:94521:15"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>The Sacrament of the Lords Supper was not by Chriſts Ordinance reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, carried about, lifted up, or worſhipped.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>You may read the two following, for they both relate to this.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="article">
               <head>ART. 29.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The wicked, and ſuch as be void of a lively Faith, although they do carnally and viſibly preſs with their Teeth (as S.</hi> Auguſtin <hi>ſaith) the Sacrament of the Body and Blood of Chriſt: yet in no wiſe are they Parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of Chriſt, but rather to their condemnation do eat and drink the Sign or Sacrament of ſo great a thing.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="article">
               <head>ART. 30.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Cup of the Lord is not to be denied to the Lay-people: For both the parts of the Lords Sacrament, by Chriſts Ordinance and Commandment, ought to be miniſtred to all Chriſtian men alike.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>What is your ſentiment of theſe three Coherent Articles, and what do you obſerve from them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I think they contain very ſound Doctrine; and I obſerve our Church throws out Tranſubſtantiation and Half Communion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing elſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>No: What Obſervations do you make from them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Such as, I think, reprehend both your Practice and Doctrine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray what are they?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Firſt; this Twenty ninth Article (which with the reſt you have ſubſcribed <hi>ex animo</hi> to be agreeable to the Word of God) declares, That <hi>wicked perſons,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Vid.</hi> Canon 36.</note> void of lively Faith, receiving the Sacrament, in no wiſe partake of Chriſt, but rather to their own condemnation.</hi> And doth not your Conſcience tell you, you have been oft ſuch a Receiver?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I bleſs God, not in the leaſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I am ſorry for it: For whoever continues in any known ſinful Courſes, (open or ſecret) is a wicked Perſon. Now to omit ſecret Impieties, not obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by Man (yet are not by any Coverts to be hid from the notice of God) your Swearing, and Drunkenneſs, and Ideleneſs are publick ſinful Courſes; and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing in theſe (as you do hitherto) I cannot learn by this Article how you can be a worthy Communicant at this Sacred Ordinance: nay, I wonder you do not tremble to think of that of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> 1 Cor. 11. <hi>He that eats and drinks unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, eats and drinks <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> judgment to himſelf.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>But before I come to the Sacrament I repent of theſe miſcarriages.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>What, Repentance without Reformation? This is new Divinity. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of Sin, and not forſake Sin? The Scriptures teach us other manner of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance than this: Repent and turn, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. and, Let the wicked forſake his way, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 55. And our Liturgy will tell you, in her Confeſſion, That true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance conſiſts in ſorrowing for Sin, ſorſaking Sin, and living ſoberly, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onſly and godly for the time to come. Beſides, had you this <hi>lively Faith in Chriſt,</hi> which our Church ſaith is neceſſary to make us worthy Receivers, I muſt tell you, it would purifie your heart, and reform your life, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.3. <hi>He that hath this hope, &amp;c.</hi> Believe it therefore, that Faith and Repentance that conſiſts with the allowed and daily practice of ſuch ſoul irregularities in the Life, will never ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you a worthy Receiver at Chriſts Table on Earth, or procure you admittance into his Kingdom in Heaven. Often read this Article, and take this Reprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Warning by it in good part; which you muſt needs do, if God give you <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> heart to reflect ſeriouſly upon your Life and Practice.—Then,</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Another thing the reading of theſe Articles brings to mind, and I would <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> is this:—Did not you once inſtigate your Church warden to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:94521:16"/>preſent a great part of the Youth of your Pariſh, for not coming to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at <hi>Eaſter?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I did ſo;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>V.</hi> Canon 112.</note> and 'tis agreeable to the Canon, which requires <hi>all Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Age of Sixteen years to receive, and to be preſented if they neglect it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe are the Words of the Canon, I know; and I know not well how to reconcile the practice of it to the Doctrine of the Church in this 28 Article. For, muſt you and I, and all the Miniſters in <hi>England,</hi> take it for an unqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble truth, That all in our ſeveral Pariſhes at Sixteen years of age have a lively Faith in Chriſt, <hi>the means whereby the Body of Chriſt is received and eaten in the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per?</hi> I am afraid, in this corrupt and prophane Age, ſcarce One in Sixteen (not to ſay a greater number) at thoſe years have this true and lively Faith.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, ſuppoſe the worſt, that they have not, what then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Then our Church faith, they cannot be worthy Receivers; nay, without this Faith, they rather eat to their condemnation: And is it not exceeding dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous then for us, by preſenting them, to fright them to do that, for the doing of which (without the breach of Charity) we may doubt and fear, not one in many of them are prepar'd or qualified?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Not at all: if they have not Faith, the Sacrament may work Faith; therefore they may be compelled.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>This is what I looked for, it being agreeable to your Doctrine, that the Sacrament is a Converting Ordinance.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Right, I am of that opinion; and are not you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I don't know, unleſs you tell me in what ſenſe you mean; whether <hi>per inſtitutionem,</hi> or <hi>per accidens?</hi> If you ſay it may be ſo by accident, as a Clap of Thunder, a Fit of Sickneſs, a great Croſs or Loſs, have by Gods ſanctifying Grace been made means of mens Converſion and Reformation, none will deny it: For, as God can work without Means, ſo by any means, as pleaſeth him. But if you ſay 'tis ſo by Inſtitution, or that the Sacrament was inſtituted by Chriſt for this end; I muſt tell you 'tis a very diſputable Point.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>My Judgment is for the latter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>You and I <hi>(Tim.)</hi> are not Men of ſuch Authority, that our particular Perſuaſion ſhould be much valued; yet I have a few things come ſuddenly to mind, that ſeem to carry ſomewhat of weight in them, to turn the Scale againſt you.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. I do not remember where 'tis ſaid in the Goſpel, that this Ordinance is a Converting Ordinance; or that it was inſtituted by Chriſt for this end; as is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſaid of the Word or Goſpel preached.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Nor do I remember when or where the Apoſtles admitted any to this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, before they were by the Preaching of the Word brought to believe in Chriſt. 'Tis ſaid of S. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Hearers, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. That they continued inſtant (with the Apoſtles) in Prayer, and Breaking of Bread <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but it was after their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, not before. Now if the Apoſtles had received it from Chriſt, (for St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, What they received they delivered, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>) That the Sacrament was appointed by Chriſt as a Converting Ordinance, it had been as proper for them to have received the unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Greeks</hi> to the Sacrament with them, as to the hearing of the Goſpel preached by them: but, I ſay, I am not adviſed that they did ſo, therefore doubtleſs they had not received any ſuch Doctrine from Chriſt: nay, if they had, they were greatly unfaithful, that they did not obey it themſelves, and alſo leave it upon record in their Writings plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as a Rule, and for the ſatisfaction of the Church of Chriſt for ever.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Inſtances of Perſons converted by this Ordinance (compared with thoſe converted by the Preaching of the Word) are ſo exceeding rare and few, as ſeem to beſpeak it not inſtituted for that end. Scarce one in an Age to be found that can ſay, he was converted firſt at the Sacrament, that this was the firſt means of enlightning his Eyes, of convincing him of Sin, of Righteouſneſs, and of Judgment; of bringing him off from his former vain Converſation, to new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heart and Life. Can you give one Inſtance in all your time? Did any one ever acknowledge or declare thus much to you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>No, in truth; but doubtleſs others can.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:94521:16"/>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>But, I ſay, I believe very few; for which I know no Reaſon can be given, if it were by Inſtitution an Ordinance of Converſion.—But,</p>
                  <p n="4">4. In the laſt place, Our Church ſeems in her Articles (which you have ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed) to countenance what I urge, rather than your Opinion: for, ſhe ſaith, a lively Faith in Chriſt is a neceſſary means of a worthy Reception, and without it we rather eat our own Condemnation. Now to be brought to a lively or true Faith in Chriſt, I take this to be Converſion; and this, ſhe ſaith, is neceſſary to thoſe who come to this Ordinance: which plainly implies, they muſt come Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts thither, or elſe they cannot be worthy Gueſts at that Feaſt.—More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, he that ſhall read the Direction of our Church to her Miniſters, in the Rubrick before the Adminiſtration of the Sacrament, touching malicious, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly, and uncharitable Perſons, and ſeriouſly contemplates her moſt ſtrict, ſevere, holy, pathetical, and Chriſtian-like Exhortations to ſuch as purpoſe to be Communicants, will diſcern, and muſt acknowledge, ſhe ſeems to favour but very little this Doctrine. And, to ſpeak the truth, I ſee no reaſon but that thoſe who are of that Opinion may open the door to the Altar as wide as they do thoſe to the Church; there being no Warrant in the Goſpel to hinder any (how wicked ſoever) from the ordinary (nay inſtituted) means of their Converſion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, admit the ſenſe of the Church be as you would have it, that the Sacrament was not inſtituted for a Converting Ordinance; what would you be at now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>At what I was before, <hi>viz.</hi> That you do not do marvellous well to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the Articles <hi>ex animo</hi> to be according to the Word of God, and then preach contrary to them. And, ſecondly, That this being granted, that the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was not inſtituted as a Converting Ordinance (to work Faith, but rather to confirm it) I cannot commend you for compelling all promiſcuouſly to receive it, only becauſe they are Sixteen years old, before you have any aſſurance or hope of their being converted, or brought to a lively Faith in Chriſt Jeſus; which the Article tells you is a very neceſſary Qualification in all Communicants, and that without it they hazard the eating to their own Condemnation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall not proceed ſo ſtrictly according to that Canon for the future; for I ſee few of my Brethren do.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>No, if all the Miniſters in the Church of <hi>England</hi> were inſpired with your zealous Spirit in this reſpect, the Preſentments at the Eccleſiaſtical Courts might for numbers vie with the late Petitioners to His Majeſty, and we will give you all the Addreſſers too into the bargain.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I believe you may; for doubtleſs they are a vaſt number.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Conſider but ſome Pariſhes in and about the City of <hi>London,</hi> in which there are ſo many thouſand at that age and upwards, that to take a perſonal and particular account of them, and draw up his Preſentment, would be work enough for the Miniſter from one <hi>Eaſter</hi> to another.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I think he would not have much time for his Study or Miniſterial Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>And I think he would have but little thanks for his pains, either from his Pariſhioners or Dioceſan; for ſuch Proceedings would gender Confuſion. And I think Viſiting the Sick, Catechiſing the Youth, and Informing the Ignorant, would be a better improving of Time, and a greater Service to our Church, than drawing up and making ſuch Preſentments. And when we muſt be doing, let us preſent the Debauched and Prophane, the Scandalous and notorious Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders againſt the Moral Law of God, rather than the ignorant Offenders againſt that Law of Man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, now you talk of improving Time, pray let us improve ours, and proceed; we have been long enough here already.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I would not weary, nor over-long detain you; for I know you ſit upon Thorns: therefore go on.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="article">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:94521:17"/>
               <head>ART. 31.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Offering of Chriſt once made, is that perfect Redemption, Propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Satisfaction for all the Sins of the whole World, both Original and Actual, and there is none other Satisfaction for Sin, but that alone. Wherefore the Sacrifices of Maſſes, in the which it was commonly ſaid, that the Prieſt did offer Chriſt for the quick and the dead, to have Remiſſion of Pain or Guilt, were blaſphemous Fables and dangerous Deceits.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>This Article deſtroys the very bulk and life of all the Romiſh Religion, namely, the Sacrifice of the Maſs. 'Tis this that promotes the Adoring of the Creature, Purgatory, and Prayer for the Dead, and all thoſe Papal Stratagems whereby his Holineſſes Coffers are cramm'd, and the Pomp and Grandeur of his whole Body Eccleſiaſtick is ſupported and maintained. Take away this, and their Religion dwindles into nothing;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vid.</hi> Saul <hi>and</hi> Samuel, <hi>p.</hi> 22.</note> the Prieſts and Jeſuits might cobble Shoes in reality to get Bread, as they ſometimes have done here and elſewhere to cover their intended Villanies: yea, the Pope himſelf would become as poor as his (pretended) Predeceſſor St. <hi>Peter.</hi> Well, this gainful and admired Device doth our Church rightly explode, as a <hi>blaſphemous Fable, and dangerous Deceit.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>And doubtleſs ſuch it is, and no better.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Then whatever Prieſt ſhall ſubſcribe to this Article, and afterwards lift up his hands to this Romiſh <hi>Babel,</hi> (without great Repentance) is a damned Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>And curſed beyond the Power of the Popes Abſolution or Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I am glad to find you ſo firm in this, and hope you will prove ſo as to the next, which thwarts another Doctrine of the Romaniſts.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>What is that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Read it, and you will be ſatisfied.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="article">
               <head>ART. 32.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons, are not commanded by Gods Law, either to vow the Eſtate of Single life, or to abſtain from Marriage: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is lawful for them, as for all other Chriſtian Men, to marry at their own diſcretion, as they ſhall judge the ſame to ſerve better to Godlineſs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Now you perceive whereto the Article tends?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, to reprehend the Doctrine of the Papiſts, which forbids Prieſts to marry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>And I am ſure our Church is in the right here, having the Scripture on her ſide.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>She hath ſo; but ſhe doth not ſay that Prieſts by the Word of God are bound to marry, or bound not to marry; but they may or may not, as in pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence or diſcretion they ſhall think fit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And as the ſame ſhall ſerve better to Godlineſs;</hi> pray put that in too.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Admit I do, yet I think 'tis as great prudence in Prieſts (and as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducive to Godlineſs, not to ſay more) to live unmarried, as married.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>In good time: Then here you prefer the Prudence of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to this of our Church. You would have done well to have read this Article before you had ſubſcribed it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>You will give me leave to ſpeak my thoughts.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Moſt freely, good <hi>Tim.</hi> I know you are a ſingle Perſon yet; but have you vow <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>petual Chaſtity (as the Papiſts call it)?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> truth, I have reſolved it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:94521:17"/>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>And if you do but believe as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> believes in this Point too, no doubt but your Reſolution or Vow will marvellouſly <hi>promote Godlineſs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>How is that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>That nothing can break or violate that Vow but Marriage.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I don't underſtand your meaning.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>The meaning is, a Prieſt having vowed Chaſtity, may if he will, and as oft as he will, frequent the publick Stews, or keep Concubines or Whores, yet be a very chaſt and honeſt Man. If a Prieſt keep an Whore at Board and at Bed, and uſe her conſtantly as if ſhe were his Wife, he is not therefore Irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar: but if he marry her, or an honeſter Woman, all the World cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him; for though ſuch Whoredom never diſables a Prieſt, yet chaſte Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage utterly ſpoils him. Now doth not this tend mightily to Godlineſs? Yea, they make Whoredom ſo ſmall a matter in a Religious Man, that they tell us; For a Monk or a Friar to lay aſide his Habit, is a Crime by which he incurs Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication; but if he lay aſide his Habit that he may commit Fornication the more expeditely, without the Incumbrances which his Monkiſh Weeds would give him in the Act, they declare him upon that account freed from Cenſure. And ſo common is this Vice among them, that <hi>Caſſander</hi> (a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Papiſt) ſaith, There is ſcarce an hundred amongſt all their Prieſts that abſtain from Women. Popiſh Coelebacy therefore is a great promoter of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is it not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis but ſome few that are ſo wicked.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis a Leproſie that runs from Head to Foot in the Eccleſiaſtical Romiſh Body. The very Popes themſelves (as Holy and Infallible as they are) have generally had a Finger in the Pye; as it were eaſie to ſhew, if time would permit: but for brevity ſake, read but a few ancient Sentences written of ſome of them, and then give me your thoughts.—As that of Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Second.
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Anxia teſticulos</hi> Pauli <hi>ne</hi> Roma <hi>requirasa</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Filia huic nata eſt, haec docet eſſe marem.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Eighth.
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Bis quatuor nocens genuit puellulos,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Totidem ſed &amp; nocens genuit puellulas.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>O</hi> Roma, <hi>poſſis hunc meritò dicere</hi> Patrem.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Of Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the Sixth.
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Non ſpado</hi> Alexander <hi>fuer at,</hi> Lucretia <hi>nempe</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Illius Conjux, nata, nuruſque fuit.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And of the Prieſts in general, one wittily writes.
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Multi vos ſanctos, multi vos dicere Patres</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Gaudent, &amp; vobis nomina tanta placent:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Aſt ego vos ſanctos non poſſum dicere;</hi> Patres</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Poſſum, cum natos vos genuiſſe ſciam.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q> What think you now of the Prudence of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in forbidding Marriage, and allowing and practiſing Whoredom? Is it preferable to the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:94521:18"/>Wiſdom and Piety of our Church, which alloweth and encourageth Marriage in her Prieſts, to prevent Fornication and Uncleanneſs? And is the former a better means to Godlineſs and Chaſtity than the latter? Surely you will change your Opinion, though not your Condition; and believe a Prieſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined by Lawful Matrimony, may be as good a Member of the Church as a Town-Bull.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet we do not read that many of the Apoſtles were married.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Not that they made uſe of the Romiſh Remedy allowed to Prieſts unmarried.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>God forbid any ſhould think ſo; they were holy Men.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>And Men in perpetual Travels, to publiſh the Goſpel to all Nations, and under ſore and continual Perſecutions. But if not many, yet if any of them took upon them the holy and honourable Eſtate of Matrimony, that is ſufficient to juſtifie this Article of our Church, encouraging her Clergy to the ſame.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>In the Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation after Marriage.</hi>
                     </note> But St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf was (ſaith our Church) a married Man: And how the Popes come to lay claim to more Prudence, Continency, and Holineſs, than was in their (pretended) Predeceſſor, I am to learn; ſtead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly believing none of them ever had ſuch Meaſures of the Spirit of Purity and Infa<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ibility as he was endowed with.—And I do farther believe, that the licentious Practices of the Romiſh Prieſts and Jeſuits of this kind (ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to their Principles) hath been a great means of promoting Debauchery to ſo high a degree amongſt us. For if a Prieſt may keep a Whore, why may not a Nobleman or a Gentleman do the like? Nay, ſome of our Lay-Hectors do not ſtick to aver, that it is more pleaſurable, more prudent, (and as lawful), to keep a Courtiſan than a Wife: And others that are married, have by theſe Doctrines of Demons been ſo perverted and drawn away to Licentiouſneſs, as to rob their Families, to maintain their Miſſes. And from whom do they learn ſuch Goſpel, but from <hi>Rome</hi> and her Agents with us? Yet we muſt believe theſe Men under an inviolable Vow of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>In troth I am of your mind; therefore I reſolve Coelebacy no farther than I find it conſiſtent with true Chaſtity and Honeſty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>And while you can keep that Reſolution, I have nothing to ſay againſt it: For you may marry, or not marry, as your Prudence ſhall direct, and as it ſhall moſt promote an holy and godly Life, ſaith our Church, to whoſe Wiſdom in this I ſubſcribe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>So ſhall I; for I think ſhe is in the right.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis but newly come on you then; for but juſt now you thought ſhe was in the wrong, and the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was in the right.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>But I ſee my Errour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis well; amend it too, and I am ſatisfied: but had you perſiſted in it, I would have read the next Article to you my ſelf, to let you ſee what Puniſhment you deſerved: But now you may proceed to it, as you have to them before.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="article">
               <head>ART. 33.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That Perſon which by open denunciation of the Church is right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cut off from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Church, and Excommunicated, ought to be taken of the whole multitude of the Faithful as an Heathen and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican, until he be openly reconciled by Penance, and received into the Church by a Judge that hath Authority thereunto.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:94521:18"/>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Methinks I tremble at the very hearing of this word <hi>Excommunication.</hi> It carrying in it the moſt ſevere and utmoſt puniſhment, the viſible Church can inflict upon any Offender.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>What think you of ſuſpenſion <hi>ab offieio &amp; beneficio,</hi> or of depoſition?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I look upon them as great Puniſhments, and ſuch as the Church may and ought upon juſt occaſion, to inflict.—But this,—Take him Goaler, nay take him Devil; all other are Fleabites to this.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>As ſevere and ſharp as 'tis, I wiſh it were more in uſe than 'tis.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Not too brisk with your Bulls, 'tis dangerous to play with edg tools. It hath been too common, to the great reproach and injury of our Church, when at the command of a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate Commiſſary, the timorous Prieſt hath delivered over ſeveral to Satan, for not anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing immediately to their names, though in Court at the ſame time. And the fault lying ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the voice of the Apparitor than any obſtinacy in them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>A light Offence truly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>But an heavy Sentence, and not to be taken off neither, without paying their Fees, as if that were the matter chiefly deſigned—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Had I been the Prieſt, I ſhould have pauſed a little, ere I had pronounced Sentence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>And any one elſe, who conſiders, to whom it belongs to Excommunicate, who are to be Excommunicated, for what cauſes, and the nature and end of Excommunication.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray for my ſatisfaction, will you ſpeak a little to theſe particulars, for I am taken with them much?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall, and as briefly and fully as I can, <hi>Ex ſubno,</hi>—I ſay 'tis to be conſidered,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. To whom it belongs to Excommunicate, and here I find the Commiſſion given to the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.17. whom no lay Chancellour or Comminary can repreſent, nor any but ſuch as are in holy Orders, as Biſhops, Prieſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And as the Conſtitution of our Church is, I think Biſhops only (who are in chief Authority) can Excommunicate, and are the fitteſt Judges when and where that a Commiſſary's Sentence is to be pa<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ed. Though our Chancellours in our ordinary Courts take upon them to be Judges, and to direct and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Prieſthood in this caſe. Which to allow, is neither better nor worſe, then to give the Government of our Church into Lay-hands—a thing which we decry'd in the Presbyterians.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. For thoſe that are liable to this Cenſure; they muſt be more than ordinary Criminals, this Cenſure is not to paſs upon common and trivial occaſions, that makes it contemptible. And I find there are three ſorts of men Excommunicable by Scripture rule. Firſt, Such as pervert the ſound Doctrine of Truth, as did <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>.20. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Such as are defiled with notorious wickedneſs, as the inceſtuous Perſon at <hi>Corinth,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1, 5. Thirdly, Such as obſtinately perſiſt in their Crimes and Offences, after a double ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition (or treble rather) <hi>privately by himſelf, after that before two or three, and if that fails, then openly before the Church, and if he will not hear the Church, then let him be to thee us an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then man, or a Publican,</hi> Matth. 18.15, 16, 17. Where our Saviour plainly teacheth us, that as this muſt be the laſt remedy, ſo he would have his Diſciples (and thoſe that ſucceed them) proceed to it with all caution and care, endeavouring firſt by all other means to gain the Offender to Repentance. Would to God all our Excommunications were always for ſuch Cauſes, and proceeded with ſuch Cautions and Endeavours. It would render both the Sentence more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable, and our Church more honourable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I am fully of your mind, for I perceive 'tis a thing of weight.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p n="3">3. That is the next particular, the Sentence it ſelf. Excommunication carries no leſs in it than the Apoſtles, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5. and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.20. a delivering to Satan.
<note place="margin">Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds <hi>Annot. on</hi> 1 Cor. 5.5.</note> Or it is a depriving the Offender of thoſe daily means, which Chriſtianity affords and ordinarily uſeth, to eject Satan and the power of his Kingdom out of the heart. Such are, 1. The Prayers of the Church. 2. The publick uſe of the Word and Doctrine of Chriſtianity (for he that is under <hi>Cerem nec decet, nec dccetur,</hi> ſays the <hi>Jews</hi>) and in the antient Chriſtian Church, they that upon Repentance were received in again, were firſt amongſt the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, hearers in the Porch. 3. The Sacrament of the Lords Supper. Now certainly ſuch a Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence as this, which deprives a man of all the Ordinances of God, and delivers him over to the Devil, is not to be paſſed againſt a profeſſing Chriſtian out of pet and humor, upon light and trivial occaſions, but for juſt Cauſes, and with greateſt deliberation and conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and for right Ends; not for revenge or filthy lucre, or barely to ſhew a Dominion and Power. But to keep the Church pure by cutting off corrupt Members, and to reclaim the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate and impenitent by this means, when all other proves ineffectual. Thus you ſee Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication (though an heavy Cenſure) is a Goſpel Inſtitution, and is appointed for high and excellent ends, and is a proper <hi>medium</hi> to thoſe ends, where 'tis not abuſed. And I muſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:94521:19"/>needs ſay, 'tis better uſed in our Church at this time, then it was ſome Years paſt. Which I hope will make it more valuable than it hath been. Many men heretofore being ſo far from dreading it as a puniſhment, that they ſought it as a priviledge, as it excluded them from our Church.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>You have given a full anſwer to my requeſt, and great ſatisfaction to my mind in this matter, which I never before ſo well conſidered.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I am glad I can gratifie you in any thing. Proceed, for it grows late.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I will.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE 34.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is not neceſſary that Traditions and Ceremonies be in all places one, or utterly alike; for at all times they have been divers, and may be changed according to the diverſity of Countreys, Times, and mens Manners, ſo that nothing be ordained againſt Gods Word. Whoſoever through his private judgment, willingly and purpoſely doth openly break the Traditions and Ceremonies of the Church, which be not repugnant to the Word of God, and be ordained and approved by common Authority, ought to be rebuked openly, (that others may fear to doe the like) as he that offendeth againſt the Common Order of the Church, and hurteth the Authority of the Magiſtrate, and woundeth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of the weak Brethren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Every Particular or National Church, hath Authority to ordain, change, and aboliſh Ceremonies or Rites of the Church, ordained only by mans Authority, ſo that all things be done to edifying.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I need not ask your thoughts of this, having had your opinion of the 20th. Article, not much different from this. So that you may read the next.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE. 35.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The ſecond Book of Homilies the ſeveral Titles whereof we have joyned under this Article, doth contain a godly and wholſome Doctrine, and neceſſary for theſe times, as doth the former Book of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, which were ſet forth in the time of</hi> Edward <hi>the 6th and therefore we judg them to be read in Churches by the Miniſters, diligently and diſtinctly, that they may be underſtanded of the People.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <list>
                  <head>The Names of the Homilies.</head>
                  <item>
                     <label>1</label> OF the right uſe of the Church.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>2</label> Againſt peril of Idolatry.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>3</label> Of repairing and keeping clean of Churches.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>4</label> Of good works, firſt of Faſting.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>5</label> Againſt Gluttony and Drunkenneſs.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>6</label> Againſt exceſs of Apparel.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>7</label> Of Prayer.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>8</label> Of the place and time of Prayer.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>9</label> That Common Prayer and Sacraments ought to be miniſtred in a known Tongue,</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>10</label> Of the reverent eſtimation of Gods Word.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>11</label> Of Alms-doing.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>12</label> Of the Nativity of Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>13</label> Of the Paſſion of Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>14</label> Of the Reſurrection of Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>15</label> Of the worthy receiving of the Sacrament of the Body and Bloud of Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>16</label> Of the Gifts of the holy Ghoſt.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>17</label> For the Rogation days.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>18</label> Of the ſtate of Matrimony.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>19</label> Of Repentance.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>20</label> Againſt Idleneſs.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>21</label> Againſt Rebellion.</item>
               </list>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe Homilies I ſuppoſe you are well acquainted with.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly no, I don't know that ever I ſaw them; I remember that ſome of our Rubricks ſometimes appoint (if there be no Sermon) an Homily ſhall be read, but underſtand not what is meant by Homily.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>It had not been amiſs you had informed your underſtanding better, before you ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, becauſe of the high Commendation the Article gives of them, which you conſent to examine, by your ſubſcription.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:94521:19"/>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>True, the Article faith they <hi>contain godly and wholſome Doctrine,</hi> and do they not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>That queſtion comes a little too late from you, yet I anſwer, they do. The Books of Homilies are (I may call them Sermons) or Methodical Writings, compoſed on ſundry ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Subjects (as you ſee here) by godly and ſober men, and were of good uſe <hi>(in thoſe times)</hi> ſaith the Article, being read diſtinctly to the People.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>But why were they Compoſed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>For the benefit of the Clergy, few of whom were able to Preach <hi>(in thoſe times)</hi> or doe any more than Read.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>How long ago was it, or in what times were they Compoſed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>The Article tells you, one Book was in <hi>Edward</hi> the 6ths time, the other about 1604.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>But why are they in uſe ſtill, what are they better Sermons, than are uſually Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in theſe times?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I think not, but far ſhort of what many of our Reverend and Learned Clergy Preach weekly. Therefore they are rarely enjoyned now, but with this <hi>Proviſo,</hi> if there be no Sermon. Whereby our Church ſaith no more than this, better an Homily than nothing. And I think our Governours in the Church ſhew their wiſdom in not requiring the conſtant uſe of them. For though (as 'tis ſaid here) they contain wholſome Doctrine, yet they are not ſo ſuitable in theſe times, as in thoſe wherein they were framed. Honeſt <hi>B. Lattimer</hi>'s Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons contain in them wholſome Doctrines; yet if one of them ſhould be read in our Churches, it would rather be matter of Ridicle than Edification to moſt of the Hearers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>It is very true, for moſt Perſons ſtand affected to their Sermons, as they do to their Garments, nothing will pleaſe them but the neweſt Faſhion—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>And I can aſſure you that's no good humor, for Truth is the ſame in any dreſs; though I confeſs old Truths in a new dreſs, look ſomewhat better than new Truths in an old one.— But I admire you never ſaw the Homilies, ſince the Canon requires every Pariſh ſhould have them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>There you have them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, I cauſed my Church-Wardens to buy them, and have diligently peruſed them, and my advice is, you doe the ſame: they are worth your reading, if it be but for this reaſon, becauſe you have approved them by ſubſcription to this Article—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>As you ſay, upon that conſideration, I may doe it, when I can light on them, but I ſhall not be at the coſt to purchaſe them my ſelf.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>As you pleaſe for that, but I hope you will read the next Article, which will be no charge to you?—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I will.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE. 36.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Book of Conſecration of Archbiſhops and Biſhops, and Ordering of Prieſts and Deacons, lately ſet forth in the time of</hi> Edward <hi>the 6th, and confirmed in the ſame time by Authority of Parliament, doth contain all things neceſſary to ſuch Conſecration and Ordering: neither hath it any thing that of it ſelf is ſuperſtitious and ungodly. And therefore whoſoever are Conſecrated or Ordered according to the Rites of that Book, ſince the ſecond Year of the aforenamed King</hi> Edward, <hi>unto this time, or hereafter ſhall be Conſecrated or Ordered according to the ſame Rites, we decree all ſuch to be rightly, orderly, and lawfully Conſecrated and Ordered.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>This Article you and I, and every Miniſter of the Church muſt heartily own, elſe he muſt diſſallow of his own Orders. Therefore we need ſpend no time here; nor much about what follows.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE. 37.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Queens Majeſty hath the chief Power in this Realm of</hi> England, <hi>and other her Dominions, unto whom the chief Government of all Eſtates of this Realm, whether they be Eccleſiaſtical or Civil, in all Cauſes doth appertain, and is not, nor ought to be ſubject to any Forreign Juriſdiction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Where we attribute to the Queens Majeſty the chief Government, by which Titles we underſtand the minds of ſome ſlanderous folks to be offended: we give not to our Princes the miniſtring either of Gods Word, or of the Sacraments, the which thing the Injunctions alſo lately ſet forth by</hi> Elizabeth <hi>our Queen do moſt plainly teſtifie: but that onely Prerogative which we ſee to have been given al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to all godly Princes in holy Scriptures by God himſelf,</hi> that is, <hi>that they ſhould rule all Eſtates and Degrees committed to their charge by God, whether they be Eccleſiaſtical or Temporal, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain with the Givil Sword the ſtubborn and evil doers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>hath no Juriſdiction in this Realm of</hi> England.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:94521:20"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>The Laws of the Realm may puniſh Chriſtian men with death for hainous and grievous Offences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is lawful for Chriſtian men, at the Commandment of the Magiſtrate, to wear weapons, and ſerve in the Wars.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>No man can refuſe to ſubſcribe this Article, that hath taken the Oath of Allegiance and Supremacy, as I know you have.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet (if I miſtake not) this is one of the three Articles, the Diſſenters would expunge from the thirty nine, and I wonder for what cauſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe it makes the King Supream in and over all perſons and things Eccleſiaſtical, as well as Civil, which moſt of Diſſenters thought was no better than to make him a Pope. Yet ſome of them I think have better conſidered it ſince, for they have lately taken the Oath of Supremacy; and I know not (if underſtood aright) how any man can refuſe it, that is not a Papiſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Then this Article may ſtand now as it is?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, and with approbation too, no doubt: for ſwearing is every whit as bad as ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing, and he that will doe the one, cannot reaſonably refuſe the other.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>But do they ſwear, as we ſubſcribe, <hi>ex animo?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Who can ſay that? I hope they do; being great pretenders to Conſcience and ſincerity. But their Practice will be the beſt indication of this, which (I would gladly believe) will prove anſwerable to their Oath and Obligation by it.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I wiſh intereſt and deſigns be not at the bottom; I ſuſpect them really.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis time and Patience muſt give you ſatisfaction, whether 'tis ſo or not, and that's all the anſwer can be given at preſent.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſay well, and for this reaſon I ſhall watch their water. And if they don't act, and walk according to the Eccleſiaſtical Laws, to which they have now obliged and ſubjected themſelves, they ſhall hear of it on both ears.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>And I think it is not amiſs to remind you, that you walk and act according to your Oaths and Obligations, leaſt your reprehenſions of them be returned with —the Devil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes Sin.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope I ſhall give them no cauſe for ſuch Repartees, having now a better underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of things than I had. And my knowledg being bettered, I truſt my practice ſhall be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Well reſolved, 'tis the beſt way (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>by well doing, to put to ſilence igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and fooliſh men.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>In troth, more Knaves than Fools, I doubt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Judge Charitably <hi>(Tim.)</hi> and as becomes a Chriſtian, think the beſt, till you ſee juſt ground to alter your opinion. And let the conſideration of your own infirmities, make you bear the more with your Brethrens.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, for Love and Charity, I believe there is not much loſt between them; for mine would ſerve me to ſee them ſubdued, and theirs to ſee the Church deſtroyed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>I perceive by your eyes, your Choler begins to riſe in your Stomach, and therefore we muſt leave this and proceed to the next Article, and ſo to a cloſe in a few words.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, have we ſo near done?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, there is but two more, and they not long neither.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I am glad of it, for I am almoſt weary.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>But I hope you don't repent of your pains?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>No, no, I'le proceed.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE. 38.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Riches and Goods of Chriſtians are not common, as touching the Right, Title, and Poſſeſſion of the ſame, as certain Anabaptiſts do falſly boaſt. Notwithſtanding, every man ought of ſuch things as he poſſeſſeth, liberally to give Alms to the poor, according to his ability.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>You are no Leveller, are you <hi>Tim?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>No.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Nor do you believe and hold that Dominion and Right, as to Worldly Riches and Poſſeſſions is founded in Grace?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>No more than I do a World in the Moon, or that <hi>Dr. O.</hi> hath a right to the Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>But you believe and teach, That all Chriſtians ought to be Charitable and Rich in good Works, and I hope you are ſo your ſelf?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:94521:20"/>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, I ſo teach, and ſo do according to my ability: for I am not ignorant of the Divine Commands to this Duty, the many gracious promiſes made to thoſe that doe it, and ſevere threatnings breathed forth againſt thoſe that neglect it.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Then I perceive you are ſound as to this Article. Read the laſt.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE. 39.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As we confeſs vain and raſh Swearing is forbidden Chriſtian men by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt and</hi> James <hi>his Apoſtle: So we judg that Chriſtian Religion doth not prohibit, but that a man may Swear when the Magiſtrate requireth, in a Cauſe of Faith and Charity, ſo it be done according to the Prophets Teaching, in Juſtice, Judgment, and Truth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>The ſumme of this laſt <hi>Article</hi> is this: That vain and raſh Oaths are unchriſtian, and forbidden by the Goſpel. And that a lawful Oath (by the ſame word) may be given and taken in Juſtice, Judgment and Truth. Or when we are lawfully called to it by a lawful Magiſtrate. Now touching the former, ſome are too forward, and as to the latter, ſome too backward. And all that I ſhall ſay here (having ſpoken ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to you of this nature already) is this, I heartily wiſh, that as ſome Diſſenters from our Church may juſtly be charged for Swearing too little; ſo that they could not as juſtly charge many of our Church with Swearing too much.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>I wiſh ſo too, the Lord grant it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Sure I am that becauſe of Oaths, ſuch as this Article forbids, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> our Land mourns, I pray God therefore, that all Chriſtians (Miniſters eſpecially) may learn of the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> to ſet a watch upon the door of their Lips, that they may not (in this kind above all) at any time offend with their Tongues.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>Now you have heard this ſhort account of the Articles of our Church, which you have ſubſcribed, give me your ſerious thoughts of them.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                  <p>In brief, and ſincerely (as I ſubſcribed them) I am convinced they are ſound and good. That thoſe Miniſters who deviate from them, in Doctrine or Practice (as I and many more have done. God forgive both me and them) are greatly to blame, and juſtly deſerve to be cenſur'd for it, by the Governours of our Church. And that ſuch as hold them firm and inviolable, Preaching and Living according to them, are not only (in regard of their ſubſcription) the moſt Conſcientious Perſon, but muſt needs be alſo the Trueſt Friends to our Church, and ſtrongeſt Foes to <hi>Rome,</hi> and all other our Churches Enemies.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tit.</speaker>
                  <p>God be thanked for this Conviction, and while you are in this good mind (with my Prayers to God that you may continue ſo) I bid you Farewel.—</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="statement">
            <head>A Friendly and Cordial Exercitation to my Brethren in the Miniſtry. Whoſe Lives are unbecoming their Function.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Call God and his Holy Angels to Witneſs, I have had many ſad and ſerious thoughts, for the Miſery and Deſtractions of our Church. And can truly ſay, the former diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is the effect and reſult of ſuch thinking; and how would my heart rejoyce, and my ſadneſs be turned into ſinging, might I conduce any thing, by what I Preach or Write to her Settlement and Union? But who can hope this, till all her Sons ſhall ſpeak, and do the ſame things; Preaching according to her Articles, and acting and living an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to her Preſcriptions, which are Sober, Righteous, and Godly? Nothing gives a greater blow, and bane to Religion, than the diſcords, and looſe lives of her Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and much more of her Miniſters. If Pride and Covetouſneſs, if Envy and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, if Slander and Cenſoriouſneſs, if Diviſion and Uncharitableneſs, if Debauchery and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:94521:21"/>Looſneſs, look ill (and are of ill Conſequence) in other men, much more in Miniſters. We are not called <hi>the Salt of the Earth,</hi> to corrupt others, <hi>Lights, to walk in Darkneſs; Stewards, to be Unfaithful,</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> to like <hi>like Devils.</hi> We cannot Sin at ſo eaſy a rate as other men, for as our evil examples do more hurt than others, ſolour doom will be more dreadful, when we come to give up our account to our Lord Jeſus, the Biſhop of our Souls, and of the Souls committed to our fruſt, whom he hath redeemed by his Precious Bloud. It is noted among King <hi>Alphonſus</hi> ſayings, that a great man cannot commit a ſmall Sin. I may ſay much more that a learned man and a Teacher of others cannot commit a ſmall Sin, or at leaſt, that Sin is great in him, which is ſmaller in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. For we Sin againſt more knowledg, and againſt more light and means of knowledg; there muſt needs therefore be more wilfulneſs in our Sins: If we Sin, 'tis becauſe we will Sin. Yea our Sins muſt needs have more Hypooriſy in them, than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men's, by how much the more we have ſpoke againſt them. O what an hainous thing is it in us, to ſtudy how to diſgrace Sin to the utmoſt, by ſetting forth the Author, Nature, and danger of Sin, thereby to make it as frightful and odious to our People as we can; and when we have done to live in it, and <hi>ſecretly</hi> cheriſh that, which we <hi>openly</hi> diſgrace? To cry it down in others and keep it (up in our ſelves, in our own Hearts and Lives? To call it publickly all to naught (beaſtly Drunkenneſs, helliſh Swearing, damned Covetouſneſs, Body and Soul deſtroying Whoredom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) and yet make it our Bedfellow and Companion; what vile Hypocriſy is this? is not this to bind heavy Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens for others, and not to touch them our ſelves with a finger? what can you ſay to this in the day of Judgment? Did you think ſtill of Sin, as you ſpake, or did you not? If you did not, why did you diſſemble? if you did, why would you keep and commit it? if Sin be evil, why do you live in it? if it be not, why do you diſſwade men from it? if it be really dangerous, how dare you venture on it? if it be not, why do you tell men ſo? if Gods threatnings be true, why do ye not fear them? if they be falſe, why do you trouble Men needleſly with them, and put them into ſuch frights without cauſe? <hi>Do you know the Judgment of God, that they that commit ſuch things are wanthy of Death, and will you do them?</hi> O my Brethren yet lot not any of us, who bear the Name of Chriſts Ambaſſadors, bear the Badge of a miſerable diſſembling Phariſee, <hi>They ſay, but do not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Sins have more perſidiouſneſs in them than other Mens. We have more engaged our ſelves againſt Sin. Beſides all our common Engagements, as Chriſtians, we have many more as Miniſters. How oft, and how earneſtly (for God's ſake, Religions ſake, and their own Souls ſake) have we called others from it, how oft have we declared the Terrors of the Lord againſt it? All theſe did imply that we renounced it our ſelves. Every Sermon, that we preach againſt it, every private Exhortation and Admonition, every Confeſſion of it in the Congregation, is a renewed engagement upon us to forſake it. Every Child that we Baptize and receive into Covenant with Chriſt, every Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Holy Supper of our Lord, wherein we call upon Men to repent and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake Sin, to renew their Covenant with God, and lead a new Life, according to his Word, doth import our own renouncing of Sin, the World, and the Devil, and our Engagement to Chriſt, and Obligation to live according to his Goſpel. And ſhall we entertain and encourage Sin in our Lives againſt all theſe Profeſſions and Teſtimonies of our own. O what Treachery and Perfidiouſneſs is this! to make ſuch a ſtir againſt Sin in the Pulpit, and yet to give it Countenance by our Practice? O 'tis this promotes Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm and Debauchery, 'tis this that caſts Contempt upon our Church, reflects great Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour upon God, and obſtructs the Power and Prevalency of the Goſpel. Methinks if we are ſincere Chriſtians (to whom the Glory of God is dearer than their Lives) it muſt needs wound us to the Heart, to hear the Name and Truth of God reproached for our ſakes. To ſee Men point to any of us and ſay, There goes a covetous Prieſt, a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Preacher, an open Tipler, a frequent Swearer, and ſecret Whoremonger. There are they that preach for Strictneſs and Ho<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>eſs, that condemn us by their Sermons, and themſelves by their Converſations. Brethren bear with me for my Plainneſs and Zeal. 'Tis good (ſaith the Apoſtle) to be zealous in a good thing. My Zeal for the Cauſe of God and Religion (which lyes bleeding amongſt us) conſtrains me.</p>
            <p>Whoſe Heart can endure to hear Men caſt the Dung of our Iniquities in the Face of the Holy Ghoſt, in the Face of the Goſpel which we Preach, and in the Face of all that deſire to fear the Lord. For if one of us, a Leader of a Flock; be but once (tho he continue not in it) enmared in a ſcandalous Crime, all the pious Miniſters, and other Godly Chriſtians round about him, ſuffer by it. For the Wicked and Ungodly (and all
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:94521:21"/>our Enemies) cry out, they are all alike: Their being nothing more common with evil Men, than for the Faults and Crimes of one Profeſſor (eſpecially if a Miniſter) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the whole Party. — O take heed therefore Brethren, in the Name of God, of every Word you ſpeak, of every Step you tread, of every Action you do: For you bear the Ark of the Lord, you are entruſted with his Honour, and dare you let it fall and trample it in the Dirt? If you do. God can find out ways enough to wipe off all that can be caſt upon him: but you will not ſo eaſily remove the Shame and Sorrow, you hereby bring upon your ſelves. Remember therefore that ſtanding Decree of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Them that honour me, I will honour, and they that deſpiſe me, ſhall be lightly eſteemed,</hi> ſaith the Lord. And know thus much, that all our Preaching and Perſuaſion of others, will prove but dreaming and trifling Hipocreſy, till we be throughly wrought upon to live according to the Word our ſelves. For he that hath not ſo ſtrong a Belief of the Word of God, and the Life to come, as will take on his own Heart from the Vanity of this World, and ſet it upon a reſolved Diligence for Salvation, it cannot be expected that he would be faithful in ſeeking the Salvation of other Men. Surely he that dares damn himſelf, dares let others alone in the way to Damnation. He that will let go his hopes of Heaven, rather than leave his worldly and ſenſual Delights, I think will hardly leave theſe for the good and ſaving of others. In reaſon we may conceive, he will have little pity on others, that is willfully cruelly to himſelf; and that he is not to be truſted with other Mens Souls, that is unfaithful to his own, and will ſell it to the Devil for the ſhort Pleaſures of Sin. I beſeech you therefore Brethren, as you tender the wellfare of your own Souls, and the Souls of others, as you would have the Church of God flouriſh, the Kingdom of Satan leſſened, and the Goſpel of our ever bleſted Lord run and be gloryfied in the Converſion of Sinners, and in the Lives and Converſations of his Saints; take heed to your ways, and become exemplary in your Lives, <hi>that others, ſeeing your good Works, may glorify our Father which is in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor would I put you only to an outward, ſober and civil Converſation, but alſo (as the means to it) to look after an inward Renovation. We, as well as other Men, have vitious and corrupt Natures, which muſt be ſanctified and renewed, or we can never be ſaved: Prove your ſelves therefore whether you be in the Faith, in Chriſt by a through Sanctification and ſerious Repentance, or not. Take heed you be not void of thoſe Graces of God's Spirits, which you offer to others and excite others to pray for and endeavour after. That you preach not the Word of Converſion to others, and your ſelves being yet unconverted, ſhould prove Caſtaways. And know that a Goſpel Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, or work of true Grace, implys not only ſober and righteous Actions, but ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified and renewed Affections: not only blameleſs Lives, but clean and pure Hearts; and you ſhall be able to judg of the one by the other. For if the inner Man be renewed, the outward Man will be reformed; where the Heart is truly ſanctified by God's Spirit, there the Life will be conformable to God's Law. — And being ſatisfied about our own Spiritual State, that it is ſafe and good, let us in our reſpective places vigorouſly endeavour the Renovation and Converſion of others, ſtudying and by all means ſtriving to fit our ſelves for ſo great a work, as theſe that are ſemble of the difficulty of it. O what Qualifications are neceſſary for us, who have ſuch a Charge upon us, as we have. He muſt not be a Babe in Knowledge, that will teach Men all thoſe myſterious things, that are neceſſary to be known in order to Salvation How many Difficulties in Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to be opened? How many obſcure Texts of Scripture to be expounded? How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Duties to be done, wherein our ſelves or others may miſcarry, if in the Manner, End, Circumſtances and Matter they be not well informed? How many Sins to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided, which without underſtanding and foreſight cannot be done? What a number of Satan's Wiles, of his fly and ſubtile Temptations, muſt we open to our Peoples Eyes, that they may eſcape them? How many weighty and yet intricate Caſes of Conſcience muſt we dayly reſolve? And can ſuch work and ſo much work be done without Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and other due Qualifications? O what ſtrong holds have we to batter, and how many of them, what ſubtile, diligent, and obſtinare reſiſtance, muſt we expect at every Heart we deal with? Prejudice hath block'd up our way, we can ſcarce procure a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient hearing, but many think ill of what we ſay, while we are ſpeaking. We cannot make a Breach in their groundleſs Hopes and carnal Peace, but Men have twenty Shifts and ſeeming Reaſons to make it up again; and as many Enemies, that are ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Friends, ready to help them. We Diſpute not with them upon equal Terms; but
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:94521:22"/>have Children to deal with that cannot underſtand, as we have diſtracted Men (in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituals) to reaſon with, that will bawl us down with rogueing Nonſence: we have A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſtical Perſons to encounter, that deny Principles; wilful and unreaſonable People, that when they are ſilenced are never the more convinced, and when they can give no Reaſon, will give you their Reſolutions. <hi>I will not believe you, nor all the Freachers in the World in this, nor change my Mind, nor alter my Courſe, ſay what you will.</hi> Like the Man <hi>Salvian</hi> had to deal with,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 4 <hi>de</hi> Guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. <hi>p.</hi> 133.</note> that being reſolved to devour a poor Man's Eſtate, and being entreated by <hi>Salvian</hi> to forbear, told him, he could not grant his Requeſt, for he had made a Vow to take it; ſo that the Preacher, <hi>&amp; ita religioſiſſimi ſceler is ratione,</hi> was fain to depart. Now when I conſider all this (and much more incumbent upon us Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, which is no Burden for a Childs Back) I cannot but break out with the Holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle and ſay, <hi>What manner of Perſons ought we to be, in all Holy Converſation and Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</hi> Lord! What manner of Perſons ought we to be in all holy Reſolutions and Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours for our great indiſpenſable and weighty work? Let us therefore with Seriouſneſs and holy Reſolutions, ſeparate our ſelves from the World, and devote our ſelves with our Might to God and the good of Souls, labouring both by our foundneſs of Doctrine and holineſs of Living, to add unto the Flock of Chriſt, the Church of God, ſuch as ſhall be ſaved. <hi>And to approve our ſelves in the ſight of all Men, to be the Lights of the World, the Ambaſſadors of Chriſt, a Choſen Generation and a Royal Prieſthood, ſhewing forth the Practices and Vertues of him, who hath called us out of Darkneſs into his marvelous Light.</hi> Which that we may all do, I conclude with that excellent Prayer of our Church, pertinent to this Exhortation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it may pleaſe thee, O Lord, to illuminato all Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons, with true knowledg and underſtanding of thy Word, and that both by their Preaching and Living they may ſet it forth, and ſhew it accordingly.</hi> — And let every one that wiſheth well to <hi>Zion,</hi> ſay. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 4. line 16. for <hi>ſin,</hi> read <hi>ſome.</hi> P. 5. l. 46. f. <hi>there is,</hi> r. <hi>therein is.</hi> P. 7. in the Margent dele <hi>Pompin.</hi> P. 10. l. 33. f. <hi>are,</hi> r. <hi>is.</hi> P. 10. l. 44. f. <hi>tongues,</hi> r. <hi>thanks.</hi> P. 13. l. 30. r. <hi>the ſin of Nature.</hi> P. 17. l. 19. f. <hi>this,</hi> r. <hi>their.</hi> P. 22. l. 58. f. <hi>the men,</hi> r. <hi>theſe men.</hi> P. 24. l. 4. f. <hi>new,</hi> r. <hi>now.</hi> P. 35. l. 26. dele <hi>a Commiſſaries.</hi> P. 35. l. 42. f. <hi>proceeded,</hi> r. <hi>preceeded.</hi> P. 36. l. laſt, f. <hi>examine,</hi> r. <hi>ex animo.</hi> P. 37. l. 27. f. <hi>there,</hi> r. <hi>then.</hi> P. 38. l. 39. f. <hi>loſt between them,</hi> r. <hi>between us.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
